<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The most delectable history of Reynard the Fox Newly corrected and purged from all grossenesse in phrase and matter. As also augmented and inlarged with sundry excellent moralls and expositions upon every severall chapter.</title>
            <title>Reynard the Fox.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 271 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831456</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831456</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35919</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60011)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35919)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2044:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The most delectable history of Reynard the Fox Newly corrected and purged from all grossenesse in phrase and matter. As also augmented and inlarged with sundry excellent moralls and expositions upon every severall chapter.</title>
                  <title>Reynard the Fox.</title>
                  <author>J. S. (John Shirley), fl. 1680-1702, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J. Bell at the east-end of Christ-Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A free adaptation and translation of: "Le roman de Renart", in prose; attributed by Wing to John Shirley (fl. 1680-1702), who published a version in heroic verse in 1681 with a slightly different title.</note>
                  <note>Title page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on A3r reads: The pleasant history of Reynard the Fox.</note>
                  <note>With a final contents leaf.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-U⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page and contents leaf torn with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The moſt delectable HISTORY OF Reynard the Fox: Newly Corrected and purged from all groſſeneſſe in Phraſe and matter.</p>
            <p>As alſo augmented and inlarged with ſundry excellent Moralls and Expoſitions upon every ſeverall Chapter.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Bell</hi> at the Eaſt-End of Chrſt-Church. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:3"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt here (courteous and friendly Reader) the Pleaſant and delightfull Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox, which in an humble and low ſtile (couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the natures of the Beaſts it treateth on) beareth in it much excellent Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and hidden wiſdom, worthy both thy regard in reading and thine applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the courſe and commercement of thy life and actions: for the aime at which it bendeth, is the overthrow of vice, and the advancement of the good and vertuous.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as hitherto it hath flowne into the World (like <hi>Sibilla's</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:4"/>looſe papers) covered with much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and darkneſſe: I have for thy more eaſe and contentment, to every ſeverall Chapter annexed the Moralls and Expoſitions of ſuch darke places, as may hold thy judgement in ſeeking to winde out a labyrinth ſo dark and curious? A labour which I doubt not but will prove both pleaſant and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, ſince as a friendly guid it will keep thy meditations from wandring aſtray, and as a pleaſant companion hold thee with ſuch delightfull diſcourſe, that thy Journey therein will neither bee long nor irkeſome: at which end if it arrive with a faire ſafety as it is faithfully and truly intended, I have the ſum of my wiſhes, and thy ſelf the proſperity, both of this and other mens indeavours.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:4"/>
            <head>The Pleaſant HISTORY OF Reynard the Fox.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1. How the <hi>Lion</hi> Proclaimed a ſolemn Feaſt at his Court, and how <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolfe and his Wife, and <hi>Curtiſe</hi> the Hound, made their firſt complaints of <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>BOVT the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> (which is commonly called Whitſontide) when the woods are in their luſty hood and gallantry, and every Trée cloathed in the gréen and white livery of glorious leaves, and ſwéet ſmelling bloſſomes, and the earth covered in her faireſt mantle of Flowers, which the Birds with much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy entertain with the delight of their harmonious ſongs.</p>
               <p>Even at this time and enterance of the luſty Spring, the <hi>Lyon</hi> the Royall King of beaſts, to celebrate this holy Feaſt-time with all triumphant cerimonie, he intended to keep open Court at his great Palace of <hi>Sanden,</hi> and to that end (by ſolemn Proclamation) makes knowne over all his Kingdome, to all Beaſts whatſoever, that upon paine to be held contemptuous, every one ſhould reſort to that great celebration: ſo that within few daies after (at the time prefixed) all Beaſts both great and
<pb facs="tcp:35919:5"/>ſmall came in infinite multitudes to the Court, only Reynard the Fox excepted, who knew himſelf guilty in ſo many treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes againſt many Beaſts, that his comming thither muſt néeds have put his life in great hazard and danger.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Now when the King had aſſembled all his Court toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there were few Beaſts found but made their ſeveral Complaints againſt the Fox, but eſpecially <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolfe, who being the firſt and principalleſt complaint, came with all his Lineage and kindred, and ſtanding before the King, ſaid in this manner.</p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:6"/>
               <p>When the Wolfe had ſpoken theſe words, there ſtood by him a little Hound whoſe name was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, made likewiſe a grievo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us complaint, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſt the Fox, ſaying, that in the extre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> inter when the froſt was moſt violent he being half <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from all manner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, had no more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> left him to ſuſtain his life, then one poore Pudding: which Pudding (he ſaid) <hi>Reynard</hi> had moſt uniuſtly taken away from him.</p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:6"/>
               <p>But the Hound could hardly let theſe words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie from his lips, when with a fiery and angry countenance, in ſprang <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat amongſt them, and falling downe before the King, ſaid; My Lord the King, I muſt confeſſe the Fox is here grievouſly complained upon, yet were other Beaſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſearched, each would have enough to do for his own clearing. Touching the complaint of <hi>Curtiſe</hi> the Hound, it was an offence committed many years ago, and though I my ſelfe complain of no injury, yet was the Pudding mine, and not his; for I got it by night out of a Mill when the Miller lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, ſo that if <hi>Curtiſe</hi> could challenge any ſhare thereof, it muſt be from mine intereſt.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Panther</hi> heard theſe words of the Cat, he ſtood forth and ſaid, Do you imagine, <hi>Tibert,</hi> that it were a juſt or a good courſe that <hi>Reynard</hi> ſhould not be complained upon? why the whole world knows he is a murtherer, a raviſher, and a thief, and that indeed he loveth not truly any creature, no not his Majeſty himſelfe, but would ſuffer his Highneſſe to loſe both Honour and renowne, ſo that he might thereby attaine to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but ſo much as the legge of a fatte Hen: I ſhall tell you what I ſaw him do yeſterday to <hi>Kyward</hi> the Hare, that now ſtandeth in the Kings protection, he promiſed unto <hi>Kyward</hi> that he would teach him his <hi>Credo,</hi> and make him a good Chaplaine, he made him come ſit between his leggs, and ſing and cry aloud <hi>Credo, Credo:</hi> my way lay thereby, and I heard the ſong: then coming nearer, I found that Mr. <hi>Reynard</hi> had left his firſt note and ſong, and began to play his old deceit for he had caught <hi>Kyward</hi> by the throat, and had I not at that time come, he had taken his life alſo, as you may ſee by the freſh wound no <hi>Kyward</hi> at this preſent. O my Lord the King, if you ſuffer this unpuniſhed, and let him go quit that hath thus broke your peace, and prophaned your dignity, and doing no right according to the judgment of your Laws, your Princely children many yeares hereafter ſhal bear the ſlander of his evill. Certainly <hi>Panther</hi> (ſaid <hi>Iſegrim</hi>) you ſay true, and it is fit they receive the benefit of Iuſtice, that deſire to live in peace.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>Howſoever a vicious man perſwades himſelf to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting himſelf from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Magiſtrate; yet he deceiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> himſelf, and by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt anima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s his enemies to be more bold in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt him, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears here by the Wolfe; who, although worſe then the Fox, yet doth he with his abſence, &amp; the ſeaſonableneſs of the time for free liberty of ſpeech, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake opportunity to ſay the worſt he can againſt him, and by his example makes others of fear full nature to do the like. And therefore let no wiſe man ſhrinke from his juſt triall, but either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his owne innocence, or elſe ſubmit to mercye for dead men and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, find ſlack Advocate;</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. 2. How <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock, ſpake for <hi>Reynard</hi> before the King.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>Have you forgot how you cheated him with the Plaiſe which he threw downe from the Cart, when you followed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loofe for fear? yet you devoured the good Plaiſe alone, and gave him no more but the great boanes, which you could not eat your ſelf: the like you did with the fat flitch of Bacon, whoſe taſte was ſo good, that your ſelfe alone did eat it up, and when my Vnckle asked his part, you anſwered him with ſcorne, Faire young man thou ſhalt have thy ſhare: but he got not any thing, albeit he wonne the Bacon with great feare and hazard; for the owner came, and caught my kinſman in a Sack, from whence he hardly eſcaped with life: many of thoſe injuries hath <hi>Iſegrim</hi> don to <hi>Reynard,</hi> which I beſeech your Lordſhips judge if they be ſufferable: again, he complaineth that my kinſman hath wronged him in his wife: 'tis true, and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe <hi>Reynard</hi> hath lien with her, yet it was ſeven yeares before <hi>Iſegrim</hi> did wed her, and if my uncle out of courteſie did her a pleaſure, what was that to him? ſhe was ſoon healed of the ſore: nor ought he to complaine of any thing not belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him; wiſedome would have concealed it, for what credit gets he by the ſlander of his wife, eſpecially when ſhe is una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieved?</p>
               <p>Now comes <hi>Kayward</hi> the Hare with his complant, which to me ſeemed but a tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, for if he will learn to read, and read not his leſſon aright, who will blame the Schoole-maſter <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> if he give him due correction? for if ſcholers be not beaten and chaſtiſed, they will never learn.</p>
               <p>Laſtly complaineth <hi>Curtiſe,</hi> that he with great paine had
<pb facs="tcp:35919:8"/>gotten a Pudding in the winter, being a ſeaſon in which vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals are hard: me thinks ſilence would have become him better for he had ſtollen it: and <hi>Malè quefiſti, &amp; malè per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didiſti,</hi> 'its fit it was evil loſt, 'twas evil wonn, who can blam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Reynard</hi> to take ſtollen goods from a thief; It is reaſon that he which underſtands the Law, and can diſcerne right, being of great and high birth as my kinſman is, do right unto the law Nay had he hanged up <hi>Curtiſe</hi> when he took him with the manner, he had offended none but the King, in doing Iuſtice without leave; wherefore for reſpect to his Majeſtie, he did it not, though he reapt little thankes for his labour: alas how do thoſe complaints hurt him; mine Vncle is a Gentleman, and a true-man, nor can he indure falſhood, he doth nothing without the counſell of the Prieſt: and I affirme, ſince my Lord the King proclaimed his peace he never thought to hurt any man: for he eateth but once a day, he liveth as a Recluſe, he chaſtiſeth his body, and weareth a ſhirt of hair cloth: it is above a yeare ſince he eat any fleſh (as I have been truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by them which came but yeſterday from him) he hath forſaken his Caſtle <hi>Malepardus,</hi> and abandoned all royaltie, a poor hermitage retaines him, hunting he hath forſworne, and his wealth he hath ſcattered, living onely by armes and good mens charities; doing infinite pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance for his ſins, ſo that he is become pale and leane with praying, and faſting, for he would faine be with God.</p>
               <p>Thus whileſt <hi>Grimberd</hi> his nephew ſtood preaching, they perceived coming downe the hill vnto them, ſtout <hi>Chante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleere</hi> the Cock, who brought upon a Beer a dead Hen, of whome <hi>Reynard</hi> had bitten off the head, and was brought to the King to have knowledge thereof.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>Vice is never without his advocate, and be a man never ſo lewde, yet he ſhall ſtill finde one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to plead for him; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where there is either greatneſſe or wealth in the offender, or any alliance of bloud to thoſe in favour, as appeares here by the Brock, which pleads for the Fox; firſt, becauſe he was of his kin, and next he was rich, &amp; able to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, here is to be obſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, the inſinuation of the Advo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate, excuſing the Foxes faults with a new form of penitence, cloaking the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> done with zeal and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, then the which no king <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> brings a good man to beliefe and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3. How <hi>Chantecleere</hi> the Cock complained of <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>Moſt mercifull and my great Lord the King, vouchſafe, I beſeech you to heare our complaint, and redre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e theſe injuries which <hi>Reynard</hi> hath unjuſtly don to me, and my children that here ſtand weeping; for ſo it is (moſt mighty Sir) that in the beginning of Aprill, when the weather was faire, I being then at the height of my pride and glory, becauſe of the great ſtock and linage I came of, and alſo in that I had eight vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſonnes, and ſeven faire daughters, which my wife had hatched, all which were ſtrong and fat, and walked in a yard well walled and fenced round about, wherein they had in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ſheds for their guarde, ſixe ſtout Maſtife Dogges, which had torne the skinnes of many wild Beaſts; ſo that my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren feared not any evil which might happen unto them: But <hi>Reynard,</hi> that falſe and diſſembling traytor, envying their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie fortune becauſe of their ſafety, many times aſſailed the walles, and gave ſuch dangerous aſſaults, that the Dogges divers times were let forth unto him, and hunted him away; yea once they light upon him, and bit him, and made him pay the price for his theft, and his torn skinne witneſſed, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe he eſcaped, the more was the pitty; yet wee were quiet of his trouble a great while after: at laſt he came in the likeneſſe of a Hermit, and brought me a Letter to reade, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with your Majeſties Seale, in which I found written, that your Highneſſe had made peace throughtout all your Realm, and that no manner of Beaſts or Fowle ſhould do injurie one to another, affirming unto me that for his own part he was become a Monke, or cloyſtred Recluſe, vowing to performe a daily penance for his ſinnes; ſhewing unto me his beads, his bookes, and the haire ſhirt next to his skinne, ſaying in humble wiſe unto me, Sir <hi>Chanticleere,</hi> never henceforth be affraid of me, for I have vowed never more to eat fleſh.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:9"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>I am now wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed old, and would onely remember my ſoule, therefore I take my leave: for I have yet my noon and my even-ſong to ſay: which ſpake, he departed, ſaying his <hi>Credo</hi> as he went, and layed him down under a Hauthorn: at this I was exceeding glad, that I tooke no heed, but went and clocked my children together, and walked without the Wall,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:10"/>which I ſhall even rue; for falſe <hi>Reynard</hi> lying under a buſh came creeping betwixt us and the gate, and ſuddainly ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one of my children, which he thruſt up in his male and bore away to my great ſorrow, for having taſted the ſweetneſſe of our fleſh, neither hunter, nor hound, can protect or keep him from us: Night and day he waites upon us with that greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that of fifteen of my children, he hath left me but four unſlaughtred, and yeſterday <hi>Coppel</hi> my daughter (which here lieth dead on the Bier) was (after her mother) by a kennel of hounds reſcued from him; This is my complaint, and this I leave to your Highneſs mercy to take pitty of me, and the loſſe of my fair children.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>When wicked men cannot compaſſe their wickedneſs by ſtrong hand, or viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt their enemies; then they ſtudy deceit and ſhifts to entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them: of all which none is ſo powerful, as the ſhew of Religion: for that working upon the eaſie beliefe of the ſimple, makes them many times ſhippe themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the rough Seas, whence there is no help but ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, as the fooliſh Cock did to believe the ſubtle Fox. Alſo in this a man may ſee, that though an evill man may be now and then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of ſome faults, yet ſtill his ſinnes will ſo dog him at the heels, that in the end he ſhall be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and lie to open Law and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as now it hapened to the Fox, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, the Brocks ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4. The Kings anſwer to the <hi>Cocks</hi> complaint, and how they ſung the <hi>Dirge.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TPen ſpake the King, Sir <hi>Grimbard,</hi> hear you this of your uncle the Recluſe? he hath faſted and prayed well: well, believe it, if I live a year, he ſhall dearely abide it: as for you <hi>Chantecleere,</hi> your complaint is heard, and ſhall be cured: to your daughter that is dead, we wil give her the right of burial, and with ſolemn Dirges bring her to the earth with wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; which finiſhed, we will conſult with our Lords, how to do you right and Iuſtice againſt the murther. Then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the <hi>Placedo Domine,</hi> with all the verſes belonging to it, which are too many to recite: and as ſoon as the Dirge was done, the body was entered, and upon it a fair Marble ſtone laid, being poliſhed as bright as glaſſe; in which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven in great letters this inſcription following, <hi>Coppell Chanticleers daughter, whom <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox hath ſlain, lieth here buried; mourn thou that re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſt it, for her death was unjuſt and lamentable.</hi> After <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the King ſent for his Lords and wiſeſt Counſellore, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> how this foul murther of <hi>Reynards</hi> might be puniſhed. In the end it was concluded that <hi>Reynard</hi> ſhould be ſent for, and without all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe to appear before the King, to anſwer theſe treſpaſſes
<pb facs="tcp:35919:10"/>
                  <figure/> ſhould be objected againſt him and that this meſſage ſhould be delivered by <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear: to all this the King gave con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, &amp; calling him before him ſaid ſir <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> it is our pleaſure that you deliver this meſſage, yet in the delivery thereof have great regard to your ſelf, for <hi>Reynard</hi> is full of policie, and knoweth how to diſſemble, flatter, and betray, he hath a world of ſnares to intangle you withall, and without great exerciſe of judgment, will make a ſcorn and mock of the beſt wiſdom
<pb facs="tcp:35919:11"/>breathing. My Lord (anſwered ſir <hi>Bruine</hi>) let me alone with <hi>Reynard,</hi> I am not ſuch a truant in diſcretion, to become a mock to his knavery: and thus full of jollitie the Bear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted: if his return be as jovial, there is no fear in his well-ſpéeding.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>Here thoſe that excuſe bad actions, may ſee how ſuch offences returne to diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>grace, becauſe evil mens vices being diſcloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the excuſe are their ſhames that make them; as it hapned now to the Brock. Alſo in the Lyon may be ſeen the effects of a good diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is expreſt in the honours and rights of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial done to the Hen, which is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of ſatisfaction for the grief her kin indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; In the Bears willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to fetch the Fox, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt how apt a malicious nature is to be imploi'd in any thing that may offend his adverſary, and how common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiments miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. How <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear ſped with <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:11"/>
               <p>THe next morning away went <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear in queſt of the Fox, armed againſt all plots of deceit whatſoever, and as he came through a dark Forreſt, in which <hi>Reynard</hi> had a by-path, which he uſed when he was hunted, he ſaw a high mountain, over which he muſt paſſe to go to <hi>Malepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus:</hi> for though <hi>Reynard</hi> have many houſes, yet <hi>Malepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> is his chiefeſt and moſt antient Caſtle, and in it he lay both for defence and eaſe: Now at laſt when <hi>Bruine</hi> was come to <hi>Malepardus,</hi> he found the gates cloſe ſhut, at which after he had knocked (ſitting on his tail) he called aloud, Sir <hi>Reynard,</hi> are you at home? I am <hi>Bruine</hi> your kinſman, whom the King hath ſent to ſummon you to the Court, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer many foul accuſations exhibited againſt you, and hath taken a great vow, that if you fail to appear to this ſummon, that your life ſhall anſwer your contempt, and your goods and honors ſhall lie confiſcate at his Highneſs mercie: Therefore fair kinſman, be adviſed by your friend, and go with me to the Court to ſhun the danger that elſe will fall upon you. <hi>Reynard</hi> lying cloſe by the gate (as his cuſtome was for the warme Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne ſake) hearing thoſe words, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted into one of his holes, for <hi>Malepardus</hi> is full of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny intricate and curious Rooms, (which labyrinth-wiſe hee could paſſe thorow, when either his danger, or the benefit of any prey required the ſame) where meditating a while with himſelf how he might counterplot and bring the Bear to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace (whom he knew loved him not) and himſelf to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at laſt he came forth and ſaid, Dear Vncle <hi>Bruine,</hi> you are exceeding welcome, pardon my ſlowneſſe in coming; for at your firſt ſpeech I was ſaying my Even-ſong: and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion muſt not be neglected: believe me he hath done you no good ſervice, nor do I think him which hath ſent you this weary and long journey, in which your much ſweat and toil, far exceeds the worth of the labour: certainly had you not come, I had to morrow been at the Court of mine own accord, yet at this time my ſorrow is much leſſened, in as much as your counſel at this preſent may return mee double benefit: Alas Couſin, could his Majeſtie finde no meaner a
<pb facs="tcp:35919:12"/>
                  <figure/> meſſenger then your noble ſelf to imploy in theſe trivial af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs? truly it appears ſtrange to me: eſpecially ſince next his royal ſelf, you are of greateſt renowne both in Blood and Riches: for my part I would we were both at Court, for I fear our journey will be exceeding troubleſome: for to ſpeak troth, ſince I made my abſtinence from Fleſh, I have eaten ſuch ſtrange new meats, that my bodie is very much diſtempered, and ſwelleth as if it would break. Alas dear Couſin (ſaid the Bear) what meat is that which maketh you ſo ill? Vncle (anſwered he) what will it profit you to know? the meat was ſimple and mean; we poor men are no Lords you know, but eat that for neceſſity, which others eat for wantonneſſe: yet not to delay you; that which I eat was honey-combs, great, full, and moſt pleaſant which compelled by hunger, I eat too unmeaſurably, and am there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by infinitely diſtempered. Ha (quoth <hi>Bruine</hi>) honey-combs? do you make ſuch ſlight reſpect of them. Nephew? why it is meat for the greateſt Emperour in the world: Fair Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew;
<pb facs="tcp:35919:12"/>help me but to ſome of that honey, and command me whilſt I live; for one little part thereof, I will be your ſervant everlaſtingly. Sure ſaid the Fox (Vncle) you but jeſt with me: but juſt with you (replied <hi>Bruine</hi>) beſhrew my heart then: for I am in that ſerious earneſt, that for one lick thereat you ſhall make me the faithful'ſt of all your kindred. Nay (ſaid the Fox) if you be in earneſt, then know I will bring you where ſo much is, that ten of you ſhall not be able to devour it at a meal, onely for your love ſake, which above all things I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, Vncle, Not ten of us (ſaid the Bear?) it is impoſſible: for had I all the honey betwixt <hi>Hibla</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> yet I could in a ſhort ſpace eat it all my ſelf. Then know Vncle (quoth the Fox) that near at hand here dwelleth a Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man named <hi>Lauferr,</hi> who is maſter of ſo much honey, that you cannot conſume in ſeven years, which for your love and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſake I will put into your ſafe poſſeſſion. <hi>Bruine</hi> mad upon the honey, ſwore, that to have but one good meal thereof, he would not onely be his faithful friend, but alſo ſtop the mouths of all his adverſaries. <hi>Reynard</hi> ſmiling at his eaſie beliefe, ſaid, If you will have ſeven tun, Vncle, you ſhall have it. Theſe words pleaſed the Bear ſo well, and made him ſo pleaſant, that he could not ſtand for laughing.</p>
               <p>Well thought the Fox, this is good fortune, ſure I will lead him where he ſhall laugh more meaſurably: and then ſaid, Vncle, we muſt delay no time, and I will ſpare no pain for your ſake, which for none of my kin I would perform. The Bear gave him many thanks, and ſo away they went, the Fox promiſing him as much honey as he could bear, but meant as many ſtrokes as he could undergo: in the end they came to <hi>Lanferts</hi> houſe, the ſight whereof made the Bear rejoice. This <hi>Lanfert</hi> was a ſtout and luſtie Carpenter, who the other day had brought into his yard a great Oak, which (as their manner is) he began to cleare, and had ſtruck into it two wedges, in ſuch wiſe, that the cloſt ſtood a great way open: at which the Fox rejoiced much, for it was anſwerable to his wiſh, ſo that with at laughing countenance he ſaid to the Bear, Behold now dear Vncle, and be careful of your
<pb facs="tcp:35919:13"/>
                  <figure/> ſelf, for within this tree is ſo much honey, that it is unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable, trie if you can get into it, yet good Vncle eat mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately: for albeit the combs are ſweet and good, yet a ſurfet is dangerous, and may be troubleſom to your bodie, which I would not for a world, ſince no harme can come to you, but muſt be my diſhonour, Sororw not for me, Nephew <hi>Reynard</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35919:13"/>ſaid the Bear) nor think me ſuch a fool, that I cannot tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per mine appetite. It is true my beſt Vncle, I was too be ſo, I pray you enter in at the end, and you ſhall finde your deſire. The Bear with all haſt entered the tree, with his two feet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and thruſt his head into the cloſt, quite over the ears: which when the Fox perceived; hee inſtantly ran and pull'd the wedges out of the tree, ſo that he lock'd the Bear faſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and then neither flattery nor anger availed the Bear, for the Nephew had by his deceit brought the Vncle into ſo falſe a priſon, that it was impoſſible by any Art to free himſelf of the ſame. Alas, what profiteth now his great ſtrength and valour? why they were both cauſes of more vexation: and finding himſelf deſtitute of all relief, he began to howl and bray, and with ſcratching and tumbling to make ſuch a noiſe, that <hi>Lanfert</hi> amazed, came haſtily out of his houſe, having in his hand a sharp hook, whileſt the Bear lay wallowing and roaring within the tree, which the Fox a far off ſeeing, hee ſaid to the Bear in ſcorn, Is the honey good (Vncle) which
<figure/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35919:14"/>you eat: how do you? eat not too much I be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ech you: plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant things are apt to ſurfet, and you may hinder your jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the Court: when <hi>Lanfert</hi> cometh (if your bellie be full) he will give you drink to digeſt it, and waſh it down your throat: and having thus ſaid, he went towards his Caſtle. But by this time, <hi>Lanfert</hi> finding the Bear faſt taken in the tree: he ran to his neighbours, and deſired them to come into his yard, for there is a Bear faſt taken there. Which being noiſed thorow all the Town, there was neither man, nor woman, nor childe, but ran thither, ſome with one weapon, and ſome with another; as Goads, Rakes, Broom-ſtaves, or what they could gather up: the Prieſt had the handle of the Croſſe; the Clerk, the holy-water ſprinkled and the Prieſt's wife Dame <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ullock</hi> with her diſtaffe, for ſhe was then ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: nay, the old Beldames came, that had nere a tooth in their heads. This armie put <hi>Bruine</hi> into a great fear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none but himſelf to withſtand them, and hearing the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the noiſe which came thundering upon him, he wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and pulled ſo extremely, that he got out his head, but left behinde him all the skin, and his ears alſo: inſomuch that never creature beheld a fouler or more deformed Beaſt; for the blood covering all his face, &amp; his hands leaving the claws and skin behinde them, nothing remained but uglineſſe; 'twas an ill market the Bear came to, for he loſt both motion and ſight, feet and eies: but notwithſtanding this torment, <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert</hi> the Prieſt, and the whole Pariſh came upon him, and ſo be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cudgell'd him about his bodie-part, that it might well be a warning to all his miſerie, to know that ever the weakeſt ſhall ſtill go moſt to the walls: This the Bear found by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, for every one exerciſed the height of their furies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; even <hi>Houghlin</hi> with the crooked legg, and <hi>Ludolf</hi> with the long broad noſe, the one with a leaden Mall, and the other with an iron whip, all to be-laſhed poor ſir <hi>Bruine,</hi> not ſo much but ſir <hi>Bertolf</hi> with the long fingers, <hi>Lanfert</hi> and <hi>Ortam</hi> did him more annoyance then all the reſt, the one havink a ſharp Welſh-hook, the other a crooked ſtaffe wel leaded at the end, which he uſed to play at ſtab-ball with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:14"/>there was <hi>Birkin,</hi> and <hi>Armes-Ablequake, Bane</hi> the Prieſt with his ſtaffe, and dame <hi>Jullocke</hi> his wife, all theſe ſo bela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured the Bear, that his life was in great danger: the poore Bear in this Maſſacre ſate and ſighed extreamly, groaning under the burthen of their ſtroaks, of which <hi>Lanferts</hi> were the greateſt, and thundered moſt dreadfully, for Dame <hi>Podge</hi> of <hi>Caſport</hi> was his Mother, &amp; his Father was <hi>Marob</hi> the Stée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-maker a paſſing ſtout man when he was alone: <hi>Bruine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of him many ſhowers of ſtones, till <hi>Lanferts</hi> Brother ruſhing before the reſt with a ſtaffe, ſtruck the Bear in the head ſuch a blow, that he could neither hear nor ſée, ſo that awaking from the aſtoniſhment, the Bear leapt into the River ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning, through a cluſter of wives there ſtanding together, of which he threw divers into the water, which was large and deep, amongſt whom the Parſons wife was one, which the Parſon ſéeing how ſhe floated like a Sea-mew, he left ſtriking the Bear, and cried to the reſt of the company, help, oh help? Dame <hi>Jullocke</hi> is in the water, help both men and women, for whoſoever ſaves her, I give free pardon of all their ſinnes and tranſgreſſions, and remit all penance impoſed whatſoever: this heard, every one left the Bear to help Dame <hi>Jullocke,</hi> which as ſoon as the Bear ſaw, he cut the ſtream and ſwam away as faſt as he could, but the Prieſt with a great noiſe purſued him, crying in his rage, Turn villain, that I may be revenged of thée, but the Bear ſwam in the ſtrength of the ſtream, and ſuſpected not his calling, for he was proud that he was ſo eſcaped from them: onely he bitterly curſt the Honey-trée, and the Fox, which had rot onely betrayed him, but had made him loſe his hood from his face, and his gloves from his fingers: in this ſort he ſwam ſome thrée miles down the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in which time he grew ſo weary, that he went on the land to get eaſe, where blood trickled down his face, he groaned, ſighed, and drew his breath ſo ſhort, as if his laſt houre had been exſpiring: Now whil'ſt theſe things were in doing, the Fox in his way home ſtole a fat Hen, and threw her into his male-and running thorow a by path that no man might perceive him, he came towards the River with infinite joy: for he ſuſpected
<pb facs="tcp:35919:15"/>that the Bear was certainly ſlainl; therefore ſaid to himſelfe, My fortune is as I wiſht it, for the greateſt enemy I had in the Court is now dead, nor can any man ſuſpect me guilty thereof, but as he ſpake theſe words, looking towards the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, he eſpied where <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear lay reſting, which ſtruck his heart with grief, and he railed againſt <hi>Landfert</hi> the Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaying, Silly fool that thou art, what mad man would have loſt ſuch good veniſon, eſpecially being ſo fat and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and for which he took no pains, for he was taken to his hand; any man would have bén proud of the fortune which thou neglecteſt. Thus fretting and chiding, he came to the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, where he found the Bear all wounded and bloody, of which <hi>Reynard</hi> was onely guilty yet in ſcorn he ſaid to the Bear, <hi>Mon Sire, Dieu vous garde.</hi> O thou foul red villains, ſaid the Bear to himſelfe, what impudence is like this? But the Fox went on with his ſpéech, and ſaid, What Vncle? have you forgot any thing at <hi>Lanfert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> or have you payed him for the honey-combes you ſtole? if you have not, it will redound much to your diſgrace, which before you ſhall undergo, I will pay him for them my ſelfe: ſure the honey was excellent good, and I know much more of the ſame price; G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Vncle, tell me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I go, into what order do you mean to enter, that you wear this new faſhoned Hood? will you be a Monk, an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot, or a Frier? ſurely he that ſhaved your crown, hath cropt your ears, alſo your fore-top is loſt, and your gloves are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; fie ſloven, go not bare-handed, they ſay you can ſing <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eccavi</hi> rarely. Theſe taunts made <hi>Bruine</hi> mad with rage; but becauſe he could not take revenge, he was content to let him talk his pleaſure: then after a ſmall reſt, he plunged again into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſwam down the ſtreame; and landed on the other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, where he began with much grief to meditate how he might get to the Court; for he had loſt his ears, his talons, and all the skin off his féet, ſo that he had a thouſand deathes followed him; he could not go, and yet of neceſſity he muſt move, that in the end compelled by extremity, he ſet his but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks on the ground, and tumbled his body over and over; ſo by degrées tumbling now half a mile, and then half a mile, in
<pb facs="tcp:35919:15"/>the end he tumbled to the Court; where divers beholding his ſtrange manner of approach, they thought ſome prodigie had come towards them, but in the end the King knew him, and grew angry, ſaying, It is Sir <hi>Bruine</hi> my ſervant, what villains have wounded him thus, or where hath he béen that he brings his death thus along with him? O my dread Soveraigne Lord the King, (cryed out the Bear) I complain mée grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly unto you: behold how I am maſſacred, which I humbly beſéech you revenge on that falſ <hi>Reynard,</hi> who for doing your royall pleaſure, hath brought me to this diſgrace and ſlaughter. Then ſaid the King, How durſt he do this? now by my crown I ſwear I will take revenge, which ſhall make the traytors tremble: whereupon the King ſent for all his Counſell, and conſulted, how, and in what ſort to proſecute againſt the Fox; where it was generally con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, that he ſhould be again ſummoned to appear and anſwer his treſpaſſes; and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſummon him they appointes to be <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat, as well for his gravity as wiſdome: all which pleaſed the King well.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>In this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Fox and the Bear, is expreſt the diſſimulation of two wicked perſons, each plotting to do the other miſchief: wherein though the wiſeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly get the victory at firſt, yet the juſt cauſe in the end pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth. In the Bears gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to eat honey, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcivious in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie of a looſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrained na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that for a minutes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, quite forget the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe and cares they have in hand. In the Fox is expreſt the cunning of wiſdome, which ever caſt out (to looſe natures) thoſe baits of delight, which being ſwallowed with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, do ever choak the ſwallower, as appeareth by the Bear, who is not onely wounded, and in danger of his life, but alſo made a mocke and ſcorne to his enemies. Alſo by the ernc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty uſed on the Beare by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, is ſhewed, how when an ill man is once ſnared in his vices, how e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of what degree ſoever from the higheſt to the loweſt, are ready to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lls they have received.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. How the King ſent <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat for <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox.</head>
               <p>THen the King called for Sir <hi>Tybert</hi> the Cat, and ſaid to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>him Sir <hi>Tybert,</hi> you ſhall go to <hi>Reynard,</hi> and ſay to him the ſecond time, and command him to appear, and anſwer his offences; for though he be cruel to other beaſts, yet to you he is courteous; aſſure him if he fail at your firſt ſummons, that I will take ſo ſevere a courſe againſt him, and his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that his example ſhal terrifie all offenders. Then ſaid <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> the Cat, My dread Lord, they were my foes which thus adviſed you, for there is nothing in me that can force him either to come, or tarry: I beſéech your Majeſty ſend ſome one of greater power, I am little and feeble: beſides if noble Sir <hi>Bruine,</hi> that is ſo ſtrong &amp; mighty, could not inforce him, what will my weakneſs avail? The King replied, It is your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:16"/>Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> I imploy, and not your ſtrength, and many prevail with Art, when violence returnes with loſt labour. Well, ſaid the Cat, ſince it is your pleaſure, it muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en make my fortune better then my heart preſageth. This <hi>Tibert</hi> made things in readineſs, and went towards <hi>Mallepardus,</hi> and in his journey, he ſaw come flying towards him one of Saint <hi>Martins</hi> Birds, to whom the Cat, cried aloud, Hail gentle bird, I beſeech thee turn thy wings and flie on my right hand: but the bird turned the contrary way, and flew on his left ſide; then grew the Cat very heavy, for he was wiſe and skilfull in Auguriſme, and knew the ſigns to bs ominous, nevertheleſſe (as many do) he armed himſelfe with better hope: and went to <hi>Mall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pardus,</hi> where he fonnd the Fox ſtanding before the Caſtle gates, to whom <hi>Tibert</hi> ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Health to my fair Couſin <hi>Reynard:</hi> ſo it is that the King by me ſummo as you to the Court in which if you fail or deferre time, there is nothing more aſſured unto you, then a cruell, and a ſuddain death. The Fox anſwered, Welcome dear cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin <hi>Tibert,</hi> I obey your command, &amp; wiſh my Lord-the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite days of happineſſe, onely let me intreat you to reſt with me to night, and take ſuch chear as my ſimple houſe affordeth, and to morrow as early as you will, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o towards the Court, for I hare no kinſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n I truſt ſo dearly as your ſelf. Here was with me the other day the trech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rous Knight Sir <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear, who look'd upon me with that tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nou cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, that I would not for the wealth of an Empire hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my perſon with him, but my dear couſin, with you I will go, were a thouſand ſickneſſes upon me. <hi>Tibert</hi> replied, You ſpeak like a noble Gentleman, and me thinks it is beſt now to go forward, for the Moon ſhines as bright as day. Nay dear couſin (ſaid the Fox) let us take day before us, ſo may we incounter with our friends the night is full of danger, and ſuſpitions. Well, ſaid the Cat, if it be your pleaſure I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, what ſhall we cat? <hi>Reynard</hi> ſaid truly my ſtore is ſmall, the beſt I have is a honey-comb too pleaſant and ſweet, what think you of it? <hi>Tibert</hi> replieth, it is meat: I little reſpect, and ſeldom eat: I had rather have one Mouſe, then all the honey-in
<pb facs="tcp:35919:16"/>
                  <hi>Europe.</hi> A mouſe ſaid <hi>Reynard</hi>) why my deare couſin heere dwelleth a Prieſt hard by, who hath a Bar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e by his houſe ſo full of mice, that I think half the Wains in the Pariſh are not able to beare them. O dear <hi>Reynard</hi> (quoth the Cat) do but lead me thither, and make me your ſervant for ever: why (ſaid the Fox) but love you mice ſo excéedingly? Beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion (quoth the Cat) why a mouſe is beyond Veniſon, or the delicateſt cates on Princes Tables: therefore conduct me thither, and command my friendſhip in any matter: had you ſlain my father, my mother, and all my kin, I would clearly forgive you.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Cat to fetch the Fox, is expreſt the care of Governours, that when they have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the prde &amp; often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation of ſuch as they did imploy, and thought diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet; that then they ſeek cut thoſe that are known wiſe, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wiſdom: is even cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvented by a greater wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in the Cats much loathneſs to go is expreſt, the unwilingneſs a wiſe man hath to meddle in dangerous matters, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they hold the party with whom they have to do, of a reach far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them; yet when au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, they muſt obey, though never ſo many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers attend.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. How <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat was deceived by <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox.</head>
               <p>THEN ſaid <hi>Reynard,</hi> Sure you do you but jeſt. No by my life, ſaid the Cat, Wel then (quoth the Fox) if you be in earneſt, I will ſo work that this night I will fill your belly; 'tis not yoſſible, ſaid the Cat: then follow me ſaid the Fox: for I will bring you to the place preſently: thus away they went with all ſpeed to the Prieſts Barne, which was well walled about with a mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>-wall, where but the night before the Fox ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> broken in, and ſtole from the Prieſt an excéed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fat Hen; at which the Prieſt was ſo angry, that he had ſet a grin or ſnare before the hole, to catch him at his next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, which the falſe Fox knew perfectly, and therefore ſaid to the Cat Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> creep in at this hole, and believe it you ſhall not tarrie a minutes ſpace, but you ſhall have more mice then you are able to devour: harke, you may hear how they péepe: when your belly is full, come again, and I will ſtay and wait for you here at this hole, that to morrow we may go together to the Court: but good Couſin ſtay not too long, for I know, my wife will hourly expect us. Then (ſaid the Cat) think you I may ſafely enter in at this hole? theſe Prieſts are wiſe, and ſubtill and couch
<pb facs="tcp:35919:17"/>
                  <figure/> their danger oft cloſe, that raſhneſs is ſoon overtaken. Why couſin <hi>Tibert</hi> (ſaid the Fox) I never ſaw you turn coward before: what man, fear you a ſhadow? The Cat aſhamed at his fear, ſprang quickly in at the hole, but was preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caught faſt by the neck in the Grin, which as ſoon as the Cat felt and perceived, he quickly leapt back againe: ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:35919:17"/>the ſnare running cloſe together, he was half ſtrangled, ſo that he began to ſtrugle, and cry out, and exclaim moſt piteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>Reynard</hi> ſtood before the hole and heard all, at which he infinitely rejoyceth, and in great ſcorn ſaid, Couſin <hi>Tibert,</hi> love you Mice? I hope they be well fed for your ſake; knew the Prieſt or Martinet of your feaſting, I know them of ſo good diſpoſition, they would bring you ſauce quickly; me thinks you ſing at your meat, is that the Court faſhion; if it be, I would <hi>Iſegſim</hi> the Wolf were coupled with you, that all my friends might be feaſted together: but all this whlie the poor Cat was faſt, and mewed ſo pitiouſly, that Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet leapt out of his bed, and cryed to his people? Ariſe, for the thief is taken that had ſtolne our Hens: With theſe words the Prieſt unfortunately roſe up, and awaked all in his houſe, crying, the Fox is taken, the Fox is taken: and ariſing ſtark naked, he gave to <hi>Jullock</hi> his wife an offering candle to light, and then came firſt to <hi>Tibert,</hi> hee ſmote him with a great ſtaffe, and after him many other: ſo that the Cat received many deadly blowes, and the anger of Martinet was ſo great, that he ſtruck out one of the Cat's eies which he did, to ſecond the naked Prieſt, thinking at one blow to daſh out the Cat's brains: but the Cat perceiving his death ſo near him, in a deſperate mood he leapt between the Prieſts leggs, and with his claws and teeth ſo faſt'ned on his genitors, that in all the great Turks <hi>Seraglio,</hi> there was not a clearer Eunuch: which when Dame <hi>Jullock</hi> his wife ſaw, ſhe cried out and ſwore, ſhe had rather have loſt the whole Offerings of ſeaven years, then that one poor little mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel: and witha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l earſt that ever the Grin was invented, and calling Martinet, See, my Son, this thy Fathers delight, and my Iewell, but it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow ſpoiled, to his ſhame, and my utter loſſe for ever: for howſoever he be cured, yet to me he can never more be comfortable. All this while <hi>Reynard</hi> ſtood before the hole, and ſaw what paſſed, and laughed ſo extreamly, that his bodie was ready to break, ſaying to Dame <hi>Jullock,</hi> Fie woman, do not torment your ſelfe ſo, the Prieſt hath loſt but one ſtone, you may yet receive due bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violence:
<pb facs="tcp:35919:18"/>
                  <figure/> there is many a Chappell in which but one Bell rings. Now whil'ſt the Fox thus ſcoffed the Prieſt's wife, the poor Prieſt fell down in a ſwound: ſo that every man left the Cat, to revive the Prieſt: which whil'ſt they were doing, the Fox returned home to <hi>Malepardus,</hi> for he imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Cat was paſt all hope to eſcape: but the poore Cat
<pb facs="tcp:35919:18"/>ſeeing all her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors buſie about the Prieſt, hée preſently began to gnaw and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the cord till he had ſheared it quite aſunder in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> one he leapt out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he hole, and went roaring &amp; tumbling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke the Bear; to the Kings Court. But before he got thither, it was fair day, and the Sunne being riſen, he entred the Court, like the pittifulleſt beaſt that ever was beheld, For by the Foxes craft his body was beaten and bruiſed, his bones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ivered and broken; one of his eyes loſt, and his skin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and mangled. This when the King beheld, and ſaw <hi>Tibert</hi> ſo pittifully mangled, he grew infinitely angry, and took counſel once more, how to revenge the injuries upon the Fox. After ſam conſultation, <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock, <hi>Reynards</hi> Siſters ſon, ſaid to the reſt of the Kings counſel, My good Lords, though my Vncle were twice ſo evil as theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints make him, yet there is remedy enough againſt his miſcheifs: therefore it is fit you do him Iuſtice as to a man of his ranck, which is, he muſt be the third time ſummoned, and then it he appear not, make him guilty of all that is laid againſt him. Then the King demanded of the Brock, whom he thought fitteſt to ſummon him or who would be ſo deſparate to hazard his hands, his eares, nay his life with one ſo tyrannous and irreligious? Truly (anſwered the Brock) if it pleaſe your Majeſty, I am that deſperate perſon, who dare adventure to carry the meſſage to my moſt ſubtill Kinſman, if your highneſs but command me.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the Fox inſnaring of the Cat is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, now when wiſe men wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> their enemies, or give credit to reconciled Friends, they evermore miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry in their deſigns; and therefore eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wiſe man ſhould ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that he grow no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fond of any thing in his enemies power; how agreeable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his nature, or his power. For the bai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of an enemie are onely gilded pills, which are fair to look on, but moſt bitter to, taſte. By the miſchief which the Prieſt receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſhewed, that they which harm watch, harm eatch, and that the trap which men now and then ſet for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gs hurt to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <hi>ſelves,</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8. How <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock was ſent to bid the Fox to the Court.</head>
               <p>THen ſaid the King, Go <hi>Grimbard,</hi> for I command you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet take heed of <hi>Reynard,</hi> for he is ſubtill and malicious. The Brock thanked his Majeſty, and ſo taking humble leave, went to <hi>Mallepardus,</hi> where he found <hi>Reynard Ermelin</hi> his wife, ſporting with their young whelps; then having ſaluted his Vncle and his Aunt, he ſaid: Take héed fair Vncle, that
<pb facs="tcp:35919:19"/>your abſence from the Court, and not more miſchief to your cauſe, then the offence doth deſerve: believe it, it is high time you appear to the Court, ſince your delay doth beget but more danger and puniſhment: the complaints againſt you are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and this is your third time of Summons; Therefore your wiſedom may tell you, that if you delay but one day further,
<figure/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35919:19"/>there is not left to you or yours any hope of mercie, for within thrée daies your Caſtle will be demoliſhed, your kindred made ſlaves, and your ſelf exempted for a publick example. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my beſt Vncle, I beſeech you recollect your wiſdom, and go with me preſently to the Court. I doubt not but your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion ſhall excuſe you, for you have paſt thorow many as eminent perils and made your foes aſhamed, whilſt the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of your cauſe hath born you ſpotleſſe from the Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. <hi>Reynard</hi> anſwered; Nephew, you ſay true, and I will be adviſed and go with you, not to anſwer offences, but in that I know the Court ſtands in need of my counſel; the Kings mercie I doubt not, if I may come to ſpeak with his Majeſty, though mine offences were ten times doubled, for I know the Court cannot ſtand without me, and that ſhall his highneſs underſtand truly: though I know I have many enemies, yet it troubles me not, for mine innocence ſhall awaken their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, and they ſhall know that in high matters of State and policie, <hi>Reynard</hi> cannot be miſſing: they may well harp up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on things, but the pith and ground muſt come from my relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it is the envie of others hath made me leave the Court, for though I know their ſhallowneſs cannot diſgrace me, yet may their multitudes oppreſs me: nevertheleſs (Nephew) I will go with you to the Court, and anſwer for my ſelf, and not hazard the welfare of my Wife and Children, the King is too mightie; and though he do me injurie, yet will I bear it with patience. This ſpoke he turn'd to his wife and ſaid Dame <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melin</hi> have care of my children, ſpecially <hi>Revnikin</hi> my young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſon for he had much of my love, and I hope will follow my ſteps; alſo <hi>Roſſell</hi> is paſſing hopeful, and I love them intirely; therefore regard them, and if I eſcape, doubt not but my love ſhall requite you. At this leave taking <hi>Ermelin</hi> wept, and her children howled; for their Lord and victualler was gone, and <hi>Malepardus</hi> left unprovided.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>In the ſending of the Brock to fetch the Fox, is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that when the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ious can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken and brought to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, then it is meet to uſe their own weapons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and with poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which can no way be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter done then by imploying their kindred, and ſuch as they moſt dearly affect to perſwade them, becauſe Affection is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Orator.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. 9. Mow <hi>Reynard</hi> ſhrove him to <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock.</head>
               <p>WHEN <hi>Reynard</hi> and <hi>Grimbard</hi> had gone a good way on their journey, <hi>Reynard</hi> ſtayed, and ſaid. Dear Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, blame me not if my heart be full of care, for my life is in great hazard, yet to blot out my ſins with repentance, and to caſt off the burthen, give me leave to ſhrive my ſelf unto you; I know you are holy, and having received penance for my ſin, my ſoul will be quiet. <hi>Grimbard</hi> bad him procéed. Then ſaid the Fox, <hi>Confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ebor tibi pater.</hi> Nay ſaid the Brock, if you will ſhrive to me, do it in Engliſh, that I may underſtand you: Then ſaid <hi>Reynard,</hi> I have grievouſly offended againſt all the Beaſts that live, and eſpecially mine Vncle <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear, whom I lately maſſacred; and <hi>Tybert</hi> the Cat whom I inſnared in a grin: I have treſpaſſed againſt <hi>Chanteclere</hi> and his Children, and have devoured ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of them; nay the King hath not been quit of my malice, for I have ſlandred him and his Queen, I have betrayed <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf. and called him Vncle, though no part of his blood ran in my veins. I made him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Monk of <hi>Elmane,</hi> where I became alſo one of the order, only to do him open miſchief I made him bind his ſoot to the bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope to teach him ring, but he p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al had like to have coſt him his life, the men of the pariſh beat and wounded him ſo ſore: after this I taught him to catch fiſh, but he was ſoundly beaten therefore, and feeleth the ſtrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s at this inſtant. I led him to ſteal Bacon at a rich Prieſt's houſe, where he fed ſo extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: that not being able to get out, where he got in, I raiſed all the Town upon him: and then went where the Prieſt was ſet at meat with a fat Hen before him: which Hen I ſnatcht away, ſo that the Prieſt cried out, Kill the Fox, for never man ſaw thing ſo ſtrange, that the Fox ſhould come into my houſe, and take my meat from before me.</p>
               <p>This is a boldneſs beyond knowledge: and with theſe words he threw his knife at me, but he miſt me, and I ran away
<pb facs="tcp:35919:20"/>
                  <figure/> whil'ſt he purſued me crying. Kill the Fox, Kill the Fox, and after him a world of people, whom I led to the place where <hi>Iſegrim</hi> was, and there I let my Hen fall, for it was too heavie for me (yet much againſt my will) and then ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ringing through a hole I got into ſafety. Now as the Prieſt tooke up the Henne, he eſpied <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> and then cried out, Strike
<pb facs="tcp:35919:21"/>
                  <figure/> friends, ſtrike, here is the Wolf, by no means let him eſcape us: Then the people came all together, with clubs, and ſtaves, and with a dreadful noiſe, giving the poor Wolf many a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blow, and ſome throwing ſtones after him, hit him ſuch mortal blows on the bodie, that the Wolf fell down as if he had bin dead, which perceived, they took him and drag'd him by
<pb facs="tcp:35919:21"/>the héels over ſtocks and ſtones, and in the end threw him into a Ditch without the Village, and there he lay all night, but how he got thence I know not. Another time I led him to a place, where I told him were ſeven Hens and a Cock, ſet on a pearch, all luſtie and fat, and hard by the place ſtood a falſe door, on which we climed: then I told him if he would creep in at the door, he ſhould finde the Hens. Then <hi>Iſegrim</hi> with much joy went laughing to the door, and entring in a little, and groping about, he ſaid, <hi>Reynard,</hi> you abuſe me; for here is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: then replied I, Vncle, they are further; and if you will have them, you muſt adventure for them: thoſe which uſed to ſit there, I my ſelf had long ſince; at this the Wolf going a little further I gave him a puſh forward, ſo that he fell down into the houſe, and his fall was ſo great, and made ſuch a noiſe, that they which were aſleep in the houſe, awaked, and cried, that ſomthing was fallen down at the trap-door; whereupon they aroſe, and lighted a candle, eſpying him, they beat and wounded him to death. Thus I brought the Wolf to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y hazards of his life, more then I can now either remember or reckon, which as they come to my minde, I will reveal to you hereafter. I have alſo grievouſly offended againſt Dame <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde</hi> his Wife of which I muſt repent me for it was highly to her diſhonour. Vncle, ſaid <hi>Grimbart,</hi> I underſtand you not, you make your ſhrift unperfect; for you ſay you have offended, but declare not in what. Pardon me, Nephew, I know you hate to hear diſhonour of Women: the truth is, I have laien with her: Thus have I told you my wickedneſſe now order my penance as ſhal ſeem fit in your diſcretion, <hi>Grimbart</hi> was both learned and wiſe, and therefore brake a rod from a tree, and ſaid, Nephew, You ſhall three times ſtrike your bodie with this rod, and then lay it down upon the ground, and ſpring three times over it without bowing of your leggs, or ſtumbling: then ſhall you take it up, and kiſſe it get fly, in ſign of meekneſs and obedience to your penance: which do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, you are abſolved of your ſins committed to this day, for I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce unto you clear remiſſion. At this the Fox was excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glad, and then <hi>Grimbart</hi> ſaid unto him: See that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
<pb facs="tcp:35919:22"/>Vncle you do good works, read your Pſalter, got<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church, faſt vigils, keep holy days, give almes, and leave your ſinfull and evill life, your theft and your treaſon, and then no doubt you ſhall attain mercy. The Fox promiſed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all this, and ſo they went together towards the Court, but a little beſides the way as they went, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a religious houſ of Nunnes, where many Geeſe, Henns, and Capons went without the wall: and as they went talking the Fox led <hi>Grim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> out of his right way to that place, and finding the Pullat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> walking without the Barn, amongſt which was a fat young Capon, which ſtraye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a little from his fellows: at which he ſuddainly leapt and caught him by the feathers, which flew about his ears; but the Capon eſcaped: which <hi>Grimbert</hi> ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſaid, Accurſed man, what will ye do, will you for a ſilly Pullet fall again into all your ſinns? miſcheife it ſelf would not do it: to which <hi>Reynard</hi> anſwered Pardon me dear. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, I had forgotten my ſelf, but I will ask forg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eneſs, and mine eye ſhall no more wander: and then they turned over
<figure/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35919:22"/>a little Bridge: but the Fox ſtill glanced his eie towards the Pullen, and could by no means refrain it; for the ill that was bred in his bones, ſtill ſtuck to his fleſh, and his minde car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his eies that way as long as he could ſee them: which the Brock noting, ſaid, Fie, diſſembling Couſin, why wander your eyes ſo after the Pullen? The Fox replied, Nephew, you do me injury ſo to miſtake me, for mine eies wandred not, but I was ſaying a <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> for the ſouls of all the Pullen and Geeſe which I have ſlain and betraied, in which devotion you hindred me. Well, ſaid <hi>Grimbart,</hi> it may be ſo, but your glances are ſuſpicious. Now by this time they were come into the way again, and made haſte towards the Court, which as ſoon as the Fox ſaw, his heart quaked for fear: for he knew well the crimes he was to anſwer, for they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and hainous.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>The ſhriſt of the Fox ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that when evill men are in danger, then they ever fain moſt religion, and by a ſhew of a penit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce, win pity from thoſe that dive not into the depth of their deceit &amp; kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, wher by though they be never ſo evill, yet they get a good name, &amp; ſteale opinion of the multitude. By the abſolution which the Brock gave the Fox, is ſhewed, how eaſily an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſimple man may be brought to believe a knaves pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp; how apt they are to forgive treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uppaſteson fained ſorrow, which indeed ſhould not be done without a more ſtrict &amp; ſevere exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. The Foxes leading the Brock by the Moneſtary and taking the, Capon, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that where wickedneſs is rooted and made as it were a habit, that there notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all hypocryſie, I will ſtill flaſh out, and a knave will be a knave in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of all perſwaſions and good counſel.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. How the <hi>Fox</hi> came to the Court, and how hee excuſed himſelf.</head>
               <p>AS ſoon as it was bruited in the Court, that <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox, and <hi>Grimbart</hi> his kinſman were arrived there, every one from the higheſt to the loweſt, prepared himſelf to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the Fox: at which <hi>Reynards</hi> heart quaked, but his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance kept the old garb, and he went as proudly as ever he was wont with his Nephew through the ſtréet, and came as gallantly into the Court, as if he had been the Kings ſon, and as clear from treſpaſſe, as the moſt innocent whatſoever: and when he came before the chair of State in which the King ſate, he ſaid. Heaven give your majeſtie glorie and renown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the Princes of the earth: I aſſure your Highneſs there was never King had a truer ſervant then my ſelf have been to you, and yet am, and ſo will die: Nevertheleſſe (my dread Lord) I know there be many in this Court that ſeek my confuſion, if they could win belief in your Majeſtie; but you ſcorn the ſlanders of malice, and although in theſe
<pb facs="tcp:35919:23"/>
                  <figure/> dayes flatterers have the moſt rooms in Princes Courts, yet with you it is not ſo, nor ſhall they reap any thing but ſhame for their labour. But the King cut him ſhort at theſe words, and ſaid, Peace traiterous <hi>Reynard,</hi> I know your diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and can expound your flatterie, but both ſhall now fail you: think you I can be caught with the muſick of your
<pb facs="tcp:35919:23"/>words? no, it hath too often deceiv'd me: the Peace which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and ſwore unto, that have you broken. And as hee would have gone forward, <hi>Chaunticleere</hi> crying out, O how have I loſt this noble Peace? Be ſtill <hi>Chanticleere</hi> (ſaid the King) and then he proceeded. Thou Devil among good ones, with what face canſt thou ſay thou inveſt me, and ſeeſt all thoſe wretched creatures readie to diſprove thee, whoſe very wounds yet ſpit bloodie defiance upon thee: and for which believe thy deareſt life ſhall anſwer. <hi>In nomine Patris, &amp;c.</hi> ſaid the Fox, My dread Lord, if <hi>Bruins</hi> crown be bloodie what is that to me? If your Majeſtie imploied him in a meſſage, and he would neglect it to ſteal Honie at the Carpenters houſe, where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his wounds, how ſhall I amend it: If revenge he ſought, why did he not take it himſelf? he is ſtrong and puiſſant, it was not for to be lookt for at my wickedneſs. As for <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat (whom I received with all friendſhip if he againſt my will or advice, will ſteal into the Prieſts Barn to cath Mice, and there loſe his eies, nay his life, wherein is mine offence? or how become I their guardian? O my dread Lord, you may doe your royall pleaſure, and how-ever mine innocence plead, yet your will may adjudg me to what death contents you: I am your vaſſaile, and have no ſupport but your mercy: I know your ſtrength and mine owne weakneſſe, and that my death can yeeld you but ſmall ſatisfaction, yet whatſoever your will is, that to me ſhall be moſt acceptable. And as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thus ſpake, <hi>Bellio</hi> the Ram ſtept forth, and his Ewe-dame <hi>Oreway</hi> and be ſought the King to heare their complaint, with them <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear, and all his mighty linage: And <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat, <hi>Iſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim</hi> the Wolfe, <hi>Kyward</hi> the Hare, and <hi>Panther</hi> the Bore, the Cammel and <hi>Bruel</hi> the Gooſe, the Kid and the Colt, <hi>Bauld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> the Aſſe, <hi>Bortel</hi> the Bul, and <hi>Hamell</hi> the Ox, the Weeſel, <hi>Chantecleere</hi> the Cock, and <hi>Pattler</hi> with all her children. All theſe with one entire noyſe cried out againſt the Fox, and ſo moved the King with their complaints, that the Fox was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and arreſted.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>In the Foxes appearing at the Court is ſhewed, that when a male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor is brought before the Juſtice, that then is the fit time for all men that have bin injured, to utter their complaints, becauſe then onely redreſſe is to be had. In the Lion is expreſt the lawfulneſſe of Juſtice, and how terrible it is to every of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuch as have the guilt of Conſcience within them. The Foxes bold behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſhews, that impudent male factors, when they are called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, make audacity their chief guard, and by railing againſt their adverſaries, do ſeek to exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate the looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their offences, but truth and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice will not bee hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winkt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. 11. How the Fox was Arreſted and judged to death</head>
               <p>UPON this Arreſt a Parliament was called, and every voice went that <hi>Reynard</hi> ſhould be executed: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he anſwered every objection ſeverally, though great Art was uſed both in one and the other; to the wonderfull admiration of all that heard him But witneſſes examined, and every proofe made pregnant, the Fox was condemned &amp; judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was given, that he ſhould be hanged till his bodie were dead. At which ſentence the Fox caſt down his head, for all his Iollity was loſt, and no flattery nor no words now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed. This done, <hi>Grimbart</hi> his Nephew, and divers others neer him in blood, (which could not indure to ſee him die) took their leave of the King &amp; departed from the Court. When the King roted what gallant young Gentlemen departed thence, all ſad and weeping, being neer of the Foxes blood and alliance, he ſaid to himſelfe, It behoveth us to take good and mature counſel; though <hi>Reynard</hi> have ſome faults, yet he hath many friends, and more vertues. As the King was thus thinking, the Cat ſaid to the Beare: Sir <hi>Bruine,</hi> and you Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> Why are you ſlow in this Execution? the Even is almoſt come, and here be mary buſhes and hedges, if he eſcape and quit himſelfe of this danger, his ſubtiltie is ſo great, that not all the Art in the World ſhal ever again intangle him: If you mean to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him, then proceed, for before the Gallowes can he made, it will be darke night. At theſe words <hi>Iſegrim</hi> remembring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſaid, There is a paire of Gallowes neere at hand (and with that fetch'd a deep ſigh) which the Cat noting, ſaid: Are you afraid ſir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> or is this execution againſt your mind? you may remember it was onely his worke, that both your brethren were hanged: and ſure had you Iudgment, you would thanke him for the ſame, and not thus ſtand trifling time. But <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> half angrie anſwered, Your anger puts out tho eye of your reaſon, yet had we a halter that would fit his
<pb facs="tcp:35919:24"/>neck, we would ſoon diſpatch him. <hi>Reynard</hi> that had been ſilent a great while, ſaid, I beſeech you ſhorten my pain; Sir
<figure/> 
                  <hi>Tibert</hi> hath a Cord ſtrong enough, in which himſelf was hang'd at the Prieſts houſe, when he bit off the Prieſts geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, beſides he can climb well and ſwift: O let him be mine
<pb facs="tcp:35919:25"/>Executioner, for it neither becometh <hi>Iſegrim</hi> nor <hi>Bruine</hi> thus to doe to their Nephew: I am sorry I live to ſee it. But ſince you are ſet to be my hangmen, play your parts, and delay not: goe before <hi>Bruine,</hi> and lead my waie; follow <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware I eſcape not: you ſaie well ſaid <hi>Bruine,</hi> and it is the beſt counſel I have heard you give. So forth they went, and <hi>Iſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim</hi> and all his friends guarded the Fox, leading him by the neck, and other parts of his bodies when the Fox felt this uſage, he was diſmaied, yet ſaid: O why do you put your ſelves (my beſt kinſemen) to this pain, to do me hurt? beleeve it I could well ask you forgiveneſſe, though my pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant unto you? yet well I know, did my Aunt your wife under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of my trouble, ſhe would for old affection ſake not ſee me thus tormented. But I am ſubject to your will, and can endure your worſt malice: as for <hi>Bruine</hi> and <hi>Tybert,</hi> I leave my revenge to juſtice, and with you the reward of Traitors, if you do not to me the worſt of your powers: I know my worſt fortune, and death can come but once unto me; I wiſh it were paſt already, for to me it is no terror: I ſaw my Father die, and how quickly he vaniſhed, therefore the worſt of death is familiar unto me. Then ſaid <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> let us go, for his curſe ſhall not light on me by delaying: So he on one ſide and <hi>Bruine</hi> on the other, led the poor Fox to the gallows; <hi>Tybert</hi> run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before with the halter, hoped to he revenged of his wrong formerly received. When they were come to the place of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, the King and Quéen, and all the reſt of the Nobilitie, took their place to ſee the Fox die. Then <hi>Reynard</hi> full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and buſily bethinking himſelf how he might eſcape that danger and how to inthral and diſgrace his proud enemies, and alſo how to draw the King on his partie, ſaying to himſelf, Though the King &amp; many others be offended with me, as they have reaſon, for I have throughly deſerved it, nevertheleſſe yet I hope to live to be their beſt friend. During this meditation the Wolf ſaid; Sir <hi>Bruine,</hi> now remember your injuries, take your revenge in a full meaſure, for the day is come wee wiſht for; <hi>Tibert,</hi> aſcend quickly and bring the rope to the <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</hi> making a running nooz, for this day you ſhall have your
<pb facs="tcp:35919:25"/>will of your enemie: and good ſir <hi>Bruine</hi> take heed he eſcape not, whilſt I my ſelfe raiſe up the Ladder. When all things were prepared, the Fox ſaid, Now may my heart be heavie, for Death ſtands now in all his horror before me, and I cannot eſcape: my dread Lord the King, and you my Sovereign Lady the Quéen, and you my Lords that ſtand to behold to ſee mee die, I beſéech you grant me this charitable Boon; that I may unlock my heart before you, and clear my ſoul of her burthens, ſo that hereafter no man may be blamed for me? which done, my death will be eaſie, and the aſſiſtance of your praiers will raiſe my ſoul to heaven.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Bear, the Wolf, and the Cat, in perſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fox to death, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelvs executioners, is ſhewed the great malice of great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt their enemies, and ſuch from whom they have received miſchief, in which they will many times rather hazard their, honours, then their reve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, ſo blind is wrath, and deformed, it makes men that are cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. The Foxes patience and mild temper ſhewes, that when men are in extremitie, they muſt make uſe of all their virtues, eſpecially meekneſſe. for that ſoon eſt doth inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate with mens natures, and drawes forth pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, whereas roughneſs ever increaſeth miſchiefe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12. How <hi>Reynard</hi> made his Confeſſion before the King.</head>
               <p>EVery creature now took compaſſion on the Fox, and ſaid his requeſt was ſmall, beſeeching the King to grant it: which was done, And then the Fox thus ſpake: Help me, Hearen: for I ſee no man here whom I have not offended: yet was this evil no natural ine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iation in me, for in my Youth I was accounted as virtuous as any breathing: this know, I have plaid with the Lambs all the day long, and took delight in their prettie bleating, yet at laſt in my plaie I bit one, and the taſte of the Blood was ſo ſweet, that ſince I could never forbear it; This liquoriſh humor drew me into the Woods amongſt the Goats, where hearing the bleating of the little Kids, I ſlew one of them, and after, two more, which ſlaughter made me ſo hardie, that then I fell to murther Hens, Geeſe, and other Pullen. And thus my crimes increaſed by cuſtom, and furie ſo poſſeſt mee, that all was fiſh which came to my net. After this in (the Winter ſeaſon) I met with <hi>Iſegrim</hi> whereas he lay hid under a hollow tree, and he unfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto me how he was my Vncle, and laid the Pedegree down ſo plain, that from that day forth we became fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows and companions: Which knot of friendſhip I may ever curſe, for then began the flood of our thefts and ſlaughters;
<pb facs="tcp:35919:26"/>hée ſtole the grat things, I the ſmall; he murthered Nobles, I the meaneſt Subjects: and in all our actions his ſhare ſtill
<figure/> was ever the greateſt: when he got a Ram, a Calf, or Wether, his furie would hardly afford me the horns to pick on: nay when he had an Oxe, or a Cow, after himſelf, his
<pb facs="tcp:35919:26"/>wife and his ſeven children were ſerved, nothing remained to me but the bare bones to pick on. This I ſpeak not in that I wanted (for it is well known I have more plate, Iewels, and coine, then twenty Carts are able to carry) but onely to ſhew his ingratitude. When the King heard him ſpeak of this infinite treaſure and riches, his heart grew inflamed with a deſire thereof: and he ſaid <hi>Reynard,</hi> where is that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you ſpeak of? The Fox anſwered, My Lord, I ſhall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly tell you, for it is true, the wealth was ſtolne, and had it not been ſtolne in that manner as it was, it had coſt your Highneſſe your life (which heavens I beſeech keep ever in their protection). When the Quéen heard that dangerous ſpeech, ſhe ſtarted, and ſaid; What dangers are theſe you ſpeak of, <hi>Reynard?</hi> I do command you upon your ſouls health, to unfold theſe doubtfull ſpeeches, and to kéep nothing concealed which concernes the life of my dread Lord. The Fox with a ſorrowfull and ſad countenance replied to the Queen, O my dread Soveraign Lady, at what infinite eaſe were I, if I might dfe at this preſent? but gracious Madam, your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration and the health of mine own ſoul ſo prevaileth with me, that I will diſcharge my conſcience, and yet ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what I will make good with the hazard of my dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. 'Tis true, the King ſhould have béen piteouſly murdred by his own people, and I muſt confeſſe by thoſe of my deareſt kindred, whom I am unwilling to accuſe, did not the health of mine own ſoul, and the fealty to the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the contrary: The King much perplext at this diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, ſaid: Is this true <hi>Reynard,</hi> which you proteſt? the Fox anſwered, Alas, my dread Lord, you ſée the caſe wherein I ſtand, and how ſmall a ſand is left in my poor glaſſe to run: Can your Majeſty imagine I will now diſſemble? what can the whole world avail me, when my ſoul periſheth? and at that he trembled and look'd ſo pitifully, that the Quéen had great compaſſion of him, and humbly beſought the King for the ſafety of his own Royall perſon to take ſome pity of the Fox and to command all his ſubjects to hold their peace, and kéep ſilent till he had ſpoke the uttermoſt of his knowledge:
<pb facs="tcp:35919:27"/>all which was preſently done, and the Fox procéeded in this manner: Since it is the pleaſure of my ſovereign Lord the King, and that his royal life lieth in the ballance with my preſent death, I will freely and boldly unfold this capital and foul treaſon, and in the relation not ſpare any guilty perſon for any reſpect whatſoever; whether it be blood, greatneſſe, or authoritie: Know then, my dread ſovereign Lord the King, that my father by a ſtrange accident, digging in the ground, found out King <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mericks</hi> treaſure; being a maſſe infinite and innumerable, of which being poſſeſt, he grew ſo proud and haughtie: that he held in ſcorn all the Beaſts of the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which before had been kinſmen and companions; at laſt he cauſed <hi>Tybert</hi> the Cat to go into the vaſte Foreſt of <hi>Arden</hi> to <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear, and to tender to him his homage and fealtie; faying, If it would pleaſe him to be King, he ſhould come into <hi>Flaunders,</hi> where he would ſhew him means how to ſet the Crown upon his head. <hi>Bruin</hi> was glad of this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage (for he was exceeding ambitious and had long thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted for ſovereignty) and thereupon came into <hi>Flaunders,</hi> where my Father received him nobly. Then preſently hée ſent for his wife <hi>Grimbart</hi> my Nephew, and for <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf, and for <hi>Tybert</hi> the Cat: then theſe five coming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéen <hi>Gaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and the village called <hi>Elfe,</hi> they held a ſelemne Council for the ſpace of a whole night: in which by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Divel, and the ſtrong confidence of my fathers riches, it was there concluded, that your Majeſtie ſhould bée forthwith murthered; which to effect, they took a ſolemn oath in this manner: The Bear, my Father, <hi>Grimbart,</hi> and the Cat, laying their hands on <hi>Iſegrims</hi> Crown, ſwore firſt to make <hi>Bruine</hi> their King, &amp; to place him in the Chair of Eſtate at <hi>Acon,</hi> and to ſet the Imperial Diadem on his head: and if by any of your Majeſties blood and alliance they ſhould bée gain-ſaied, that then my Father with his treaſure ſhould hire thoſe which ſhould utterly chaſe and root them out of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. Now after this determination held and finiſhed, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that my Nephew <hi>Grimbart</hi> being on a time high flown with wine, he diſcovered this damnable plot to dame <hi>Slo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35919:27"/>his wife, commanded her upon her life to kéep ſecret the ſame: but ſhe forgotfull of her charge, diſcloſed it in confeſſion to my wife, as they went a Pilgrimage over an Heath, with like conjuration of ſecreſie: but ſhe (women-like) contained it no longer then till ſhe met with me, and gave me a ful know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all that paſſed; yet ſo, as by all meanes I muſt kéep it ſecret too: for ſhe had ſworn by the three Kings of <hi>Cullen</hi> never to diſcloſe it: and withall, ſhe gave me ſuch aſſurance by certain tokens, that I right well ſcund all was true which ſhe had ſpoken, inſomuch, that the very affright thereof made my hair ſtand upright, and my heart became like Lead, cold and heavy in my boſome, which made me call to mind the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Frogs, who being free without ſubjection, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and deſired they might have a King to rule and govern over them, and he preſently ſent them a Stork, which eat and devoured them up: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that by his tyranny they became the moſt miſerable of all creatures; then they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained again to <hi>Jupiter</hi> for redreſſe, but it was then too late; for they that could not be content with their fréedom, muſt now of neceſſity ſuffer in thraldome.</p>
               <p>Thus I feared it might happen with us, and thus I ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed for your Majeſty, although you little reſpect my grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: I know that ambition of the Bear, and his tyranny is ſo great; that ſhould the Government come into his hands, (as heaven forbid) the whole Common-wealth will he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed? Beſides, I know your Majeſtie of ſo royall and Princely birth: ſo mighty, ſo gracious, and ſo mercifull, that it had been a damnable exchange, to have ſeen a ravenous Bear to ſit in the throne of a royall Lyon; for there is in the Bear, and in his generation, more prodigall looſneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie, then in any Beaſt whatſoever. But to proceed, from this ſorrow, I began to meditate how I might undo my Fathers falſe and wicked conſpiracies, who ſought to bring a baſe Traitor and a ſlave into the throne Emperiall: for I well perceived as long as he held the Treaſure, there was a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of depoſing your Majeſty, and this troubled my thought excéedingly, ſo that I laboured how I might find out where
<pb facs="tcp:35919:28"/>my Fathers Treaſure was hid, and to that end I watcht and attended night and day in the Woods, in the Buſhes, and in
<figure/> the open fields: nay, in all places whereſoever my father laid his eyes, there was I ever watching and attending. Now it hapened on a time as I was laid down flat on the ground, I
<pb facs="tcp:35919:28"/>ſaw my father come running out of a hole, and as ſoon as he was come out, he gazed round about him, to ſee if any diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him; then ſeeing the coaſt clear, he ſtopped the hole with ſand, and made it ſo even, ſmooth and plain, that no curious rye could diſcerne a difference betwixt it and the other earth: and where the print of his foot remained, that with his tail he ſtroked over; and with his mouth ſo ſmoothed it that no man might perceive it: and indéed that and many other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties, I learned of him there at that inſtant: when he had thus finiſhed away he went towards the village about his private affaires: then went I preſently towards the hole, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his ſubtiltie, I quickly found it out, then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres I the Cave, where I found that innumerable quantity of treaſure, which cannot bée expreſſed: which ſound, I took <hi>Ermelin</hi> my wife to help me, and wée ceaſt not day nor night, with infinite great toyle and labour, to carry and convey away this treaſure to another place, much more convenient for us, where we laid it ſafe from the ſearch of any creature. Now during the time that my wife and I were thus imployed, my father was in conſultation with the reſt of the traytors about the death of the King: in which conſultation it was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf ſhould travaile over all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and promiſe to all Beaſts that would take wages, and acknowledge <hi>Bruine</hi> for their ſoveraigne, and defend his ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, a full yeares pay beforehand. And in this journey my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accompanied him, carrying letters Patents ſigned to that purpoſe, little ſuſpecting that he was rob'd of the wealth which ſhould ſupplie his treaſon: When this negotiation was fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed betwéen <hi>Elve</hi> and <hi>Soame,</hi> and a world of valiant ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers raiſed againſt the begining of the next ſpring: then they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Bruine</hi> and his conſorts, to whom they declared the many perills they had eſcaped in the Dukedome of <hi>Saxony:</hi> where they were purſued by Huntſmen and Hounds, ſo as they hardly eſcaped with life: after this relation they ſhewed <hi>Eruine</hi> the muſter-rolls, which pleaſed him exceeding much, for there was of <hi>Iſegrims</hi> lineage about twelve hundred ſworne to the actions, beſides the Beares own kindred,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:29"/>the Foxes, the Cats, and the Daſſens, all which would be in readineſſe upon an hours warning. All this I found out (I praiſe Heaven) by perfect intelligence: now things being brought to this perfection, my father went to his Cave of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: but when he found it open, ſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'d and ranſackt, it is not in me to expreſſe the infinite agony and ſorrow he fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that grief converting to madneſſe, and madneſſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation: ſuddainly he went to the next trée and hanged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>Thus by my Art onely was the Treaſon of <hi>Bruine</hi> defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for which I now ſuffer: from hence ſprang all misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune as thus: Theſe foule traytors <hi>Bruine</hi> and <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Kings privateſt Counſell, and ſitting in high and great Authority, tread upon me poor <hi>Reynard,</hi> and work my diſgrace: notwithſtanding for your Majeſties ſake, I have loſt my naturall Father. O my dread Lord! what is he, or who can tender you a better affection, thus to loſe himſelf to ſave you? The King and Quéen having great hope to get this ineſtimable treaſure from <hi>Reynard,</hi> tooke him from the Gibbet, and intreated him to unfold where this great trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was. But the Fox replied, O my Lord, ſhall I make mine enemies my heirs? ſhall theſe Traytors which take away my life, and would devour yours, be poſſeſt of the good I injoy? No, that's a madneſs I'le never dye guilty of. Then ſaid the Quéen, fear not <hi>Reynard,</hi> the King ſhall ſave your life, and grant you pardon, and you ſhall henceforth ſwear Faith and true Allegeance to his Majeſty. The Fox an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: Deareſt Madam, if the King out of his Royall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will give credit to my truth and forgive my former offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; there was never King ſo rich as I will make him. Then the King ſtaying the Quéen, ſaid: Madam, will you believe the Fox? know you not that it is his naturall quality to lye ſteal, and deceive? The Quéen anſwered, My dear Lord, now you may boldly believe him, for howſoever in his proſperity he was full of errors, yet now you may ſee he is changed? why he ſpareth not to accuſe his own father, nay <hi>Grimbard</hi> his deareſt Nephew and kinſman; had he diſſembled, he might
<pb facs="tcp:35919:29"/>have laid his imputations on other Beaſts, and not on thoſe he loveth moſt intirely. Well Madam (ſaid the King) you ſhall at this time rule me, and all the offences of the Fox I will clearly pardon: yet with this Proteſtation, That if ever again he offend in the ſmalleſt crime whatſoever, that not onely himſelf, but his whole generation I will utterly root out of my Dominions. The Fox looked ſadly when the King ſpake thus (but was inwardly moſt infinitely glad at his heart, and ſaid, My dread Lord, it were a huge ſhame in me, ſhould I ſpeak any untruths in this great preſence. Then the King taking a ſtraw from the ground, pardoned the Fox of all his treſpaſſes which either he, or his Father had ever committed: If the Fox now began to ſmile, it was no wonder, the ſwéetneſſe of life required it: yet he fell down before the King and Queén, and humbly thanked them for their mercie, proteſting that for that favour he would make them the richeſt Princes in the world. And at theſe words the Fox took up a ſtraw, and profered it unto the King, and ſaid to him; My dread Lord, I beſeech your Majeſtie to receive this pledg as a ſurrender unto your Majeſtie of all the Treaſure that the great King <hi>Ermerick</hi> was maſter of, with which I fréely infeoffe you out of my meer voluntary and frée motion. At theſe words the King received the ſtraw, and ſmiling, gave the Fox great thanks for the ſame. But the Fox laughed out-right to think of the abuſe. From that day for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward no mans counſel prevailed with the King as the Foxes; which the Fox ſeeing, ſaid to the King: My gracious Lord! you ſhall underſtand, that at the Weſt-ſide of <hi>Flanders</hi> there ſtandeth a Wood called <hi>Huſterloe,</hi> near which run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a River named <hi>Crekenpit</hi> this is a Wilderneſſe ſo vaſte, and unpaſſable, that hardly in all the year there cometh either man or woman in the ſame. In it I have hid this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whither I would have your Majeſtie and the Queen to go, for I know none but your ſelves whom I dare truſt in ſo great a deſign: and when your Highneſs comes thither, you ſhall finde two Birchin trees growing by the pit, into which you ſhall enter, and there you ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l finde the Treaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:30"/>which conſiſteth of the Coine, rich Iewels, and the wealthy Crown which King <hi>Ermerick</hi> wore. With which Crown <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear ſhould have been Crowned, if his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon had ſucceeded according to his determination: there ſhall you ſée alſo many rich and coſtly precious ſtones, of which when you are poſſeſt, then remember the love of your ſervant <hi>Reynard.</hi> The King anſwered, Sir <hi>Reynard,</hi> you muſt your ſelf help to digge for this Treaſure, for elſe I ſhall never finde it. I have heard named <hi>Paris, London, Acon,</hi> and <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> but <hi>Crekenpit</hi> I never heard of: therefore I fear you diſſemble. The Fox bluſhed at thoſe words, yet with a bold countenance he ſaid: is your Majeſty ſo doubtfull of my faith? nay then I will approve my words by publique teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony: and with that he called forth <hi>Kayward</hi> the Hare, from amongſt the reſt of the Beaſts, and commanded him to come before the King, charging him upon his Faith and Allegiance which he bore to the King and Quéen, to anſwer truly to ſuch queſtions as he ſhould ask him. The Hare anſwered, I will ſpeak truth in all things, though I were ſure to dye for the ſame. Then the Fox ſaid: Know you not where <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenpit</hi> ſtandeth? Yes ſaid the Hare, I have known it any time this dozen yeares, it ſtandeth in a wood called <hi>Huſſerloe,</hi> upon a vaſt and wide Wilderneſſe, where I have in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ured much torment both of hunger and cold: Beſides, it was there where Father <hi>Simony</hi> the Fryer made falſe Coine, with which he ſupported himſelfe and his fellows. Yet that was before I and <hi>Ring</hi> the Hound became companions. Well ſaid the Fox, you have ſpoken ſufficiently: go to your place again: ſo away went the Hare, Then ſaid the Fox. My ſoveraign Lord the King, what ſay you now to my relation, am I worthy of your beliefe or no? the King ſaid, Yes <hi>Reynard,</hi> and I beſeech thee excuſe my Iealouſies, it was my ignorance which did thee evill: therefore forthwith make preparation that we may go to the pit where this Treaſure lyeth. The Fox anſwered, Alas my Lord, do you imagine that I would ſain go with you: If it were ſo that I might go without your diſhonour, which I cannot do; For you ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:30"/>(though it be my diſgrace) that when <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf in the Devills name, would needs grow religious and turn a Monke: that then the permiſion of meat which was for ſix Monks; was too little for him alone. Whereupon he complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo pitifully unto me, that I commiſerating his caſe, (being my kinſman) gave him conſell to run away, which he did: Whereupon I ſtand accurſed, and excommunicated under the Popes ſentence: and am determined to morrow as ſoon as the Sun ariſeth, to take my way towards <hi>Rome</hi> to be abſolved, and from <hi>Rome</hi> I intend to croſſe the Seas to the Holy land; and will never return again to my native Country: till I have done ſo much good, and ſatisfied for my ſins; that I may with honour and reputation attend on your Highneſſes perſon. The King hearing this, ſaid: Since you ſtand accurſed in the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Church, I may not have you about me, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will at this time take <hi>Kayward</hi> the Hare, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with me to <hi>Crekenpit:</hi> and onely command you <hi>Reynard,</hi> as you reſpect my favour, to clear your ſelf of his Holineſſes curſe. My Lord (ſaid the Fox) it is the onely reaſon of my going to <hi>Rome,</hi> neither will I reſt night nor day, till I have gotten a full abſolution: the courſe you take is good (ſaid the King) go on and proſper in your intent and purpoſe.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the Foxes confeſſion and accuſation of his enemies, is expreſſed a three fold ſubtilty in the Fox: Firſt, by his voluntary confeſſion of his faults, is ſhewed his ſorrow for the ſame, and the little hope he had of life, which pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing into the weak nature of the Queen, being a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to pity, begot much compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards him. 2. The accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of thoſe whom he was known moſt aſſuredly to love, was a means to draw belief to that he ſpake. 3. The inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the life of the King, and making the treaſon ſo foul, was a way to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright the Queen, and others of the tenderneſſe of heart, and to bring his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies into diſgrace and ſcandal, where in the Fox ſheweth, that he which will ſlander, or wil have any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth believed: muſt firſt ſtrengthen his opinion with pity, then get belief, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe his miſchief, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all which a wiſe man will ſhut his eares as the Lyon did: If he be not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by thoſe he loves, as the Lyon was by the Queen and his own cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, in deſiring that infinite trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, then which there is nothing draws a man ſooner to the belief of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth and of falſhood: for what a man deſires, that his own deſire will make him credit, and where ſuch credit is given, there common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the wicked eſcape from puniſhment, as here it fell out with the Fox.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 13 How <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox was honoured of all Beaſts by the Kings Commandment.</head>
               <p>AS ſoon as this conference was ended, the royall King mounted upon his high Throne made in manner of a ſcaffold, made of fair ſquared Stone, and then commanded a generall ſilence amongſt all his Subjects and that every one ſhould take his place according to his Birth, or dignity in Office, onely the Fox was placed between the King and the Qéen. Then ſaid the King: Hear all you Noble men, Knights, Gentlemen, and others of inferiour quality: This <hi>Reynard,</hi> one of the chief and ſupreame Officers of my
<pb facs="tcp:35919:31"/>houſhould, whoſe offences had brought him to the leaſt reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his life; as being in the hands of the Law and Iuſtice:
<figure/> hath this day in requitall of thoſe Injuries, done that Noble and worthy, ſervice to the State, that both my ſelfe and my Quéen, ſtand bound to render him our beſt grace and favour.
<pb facs="tcp:35919:31"/>Therefore know, that for divers things beſt known unto our ſelves, we have freely given pardon to all his offences, and reſtored back to him whatſoever to us was confiſcate: therefore henceforth I command all of you, upon the pain and hazard of your deareſt lives, that you fail not from this day forward to do all reverence and honour, not onely to <hi>Reynard</hi> himſelf, but alſo to his Wife and Children, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever or whereſoever you ſhall meet them, whether by night, or by day: not that any one hereafter be ſo audacious, as to trouble mine ears with any more complaints of him: for his wickedneſſe he hath caſt behinde him, and will no more be guilty of wrong doing: which to effect the better, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row very early he taketh his journey towards <hi>Rome,</hi> where from the Pope he will purchaſe a free Pardon and Indulgence for all his offences, and then on Pilgrimage to the Holy-land. This ſpeech when <hi>Tiſellin</hi> the Raven heard, he flew to <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, Iſegrim,</hi> and <hi>Tibert,</hi> and ſaid; Wretched creature! how are your fortunes changed? or how can you indure to hear theſe ttioings? Why <hi>Reynard</hi> is now a Courtier, a Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; nay the prime Favorite: his offences are forgiven, and you are all betraied. And ſold unto bondage. <hi>Iſegrim</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, It is impoſſible <hi>Tiſellin,</hi> nor can ſuch a thing be ſuffered: do not deceive your ſelves (ſaid the Raven) for it is true as that now I ſpeak it. Then went the Wolf and the Bear to the King; but the Cat ſtaid, and was ſo ſore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with the newes, that to purchaſe the Foxes friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip again, ſhe would not onely have forgiven the exile re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but willingly have run into a ſecond hazard. But now <hi>Iſegrim</hi> with great majeſtie and pride tracing over the Fields, came before the King and Quéen, and with moſt bitter and cruel words, inveighed againſt the Fox in ſuch a paſſionate and impudent manner, that the King being infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely moved with diſpleaſure, cauſed the Wolf and the Bear to be preſently arreſted upon high Treaſon: which ſuddenly was done with all violence and fury, and they were bound hand and foot ſo faſt, that they could neither ſtir nor move from the place where they were couched. Now when the Fox
<pb facs="tcp:35919:32"/>had thus inthralled and intangled them, he ſo laboured with the Quéen, that he got leave to have ſo much of the Bears skin, as would make him a large Scrip for his Iourney:
<figure/> Which granted, he wanted nothing but a ſtrong pair of Shoo's to defend his feet from the ſtones in his travel:
<pb facs="tcp:35919:32"/>Whereupon he ſaid to the Quéen; Madam, I am your Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim; and if it would pleaſe your Majeſtie but to take it into your conſideration, you ſhall find that Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> hath a pair of excellent long laſting ones, which would you vouchſafe to beſtow upon me, I would pray for your Majeſties ſoul in all my travel, above my charitable devotion. Alſo mine Aunt, dame <hi>Arſewinde,</hi> hath other two ſhoo's, which would your Majeſtie beſtow upon me, I ſhould be moſt infinitely bound to you, nor ſhould you do to her any wrong, becauſe ſhe goes ſeldom abroad. The Quéen replied, <hi>Reynard,</hi> I cannot perceive how you can want ſuch ſhoo's, for your journey is full of labour and difficulty, both in reſpect of the ſtonie mountains, and the gravelly waies, and thereforè you ſhall have (though it touch their life never ſo nearly) from each of them a pair of Shoo's to accompliſh and finiſh your journey.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By this honour done to the Fox, you may ſee, that when policy and wiſdome get the upper hand of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, it never reſteth till it maketh known to the world the greaneſſe of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, both to expreſſe their ambition, as alſo to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate their crimes, and keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heir foes in aw with the goodly ſhews of new grace and favour. By the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Raven, is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they jelouſie and fear of the weaker ſort. and how in their troubles they flie to the Heads of faction, and ſtir them (with their owne ſafteies) to prevent evils. By the Wolf and the Bears commitment, is ſhewed, that when men complain in unſeaſonable times, they ever run them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into moſt apparent and grievous miſchiefs.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 14. How <hi>Iſegrim</hi> and his wife <hi>Arſewind</hi> had their ſhoo's plucks off for <hi>Reynard</hi> to wear to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter the Fox had made this petition, <hi>Iſegrim</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and his ſhoo's pulled off in moſt cruel and violent manner, ſo that all the veins and ſinews lay naked, nor durſt the poor maſſacred Wolf either complain or reſiſt. After he had been thus tormented, then dame <hi>Arſewinde</hi> his wife was uſed on the ſame manner on her hinder-féet, as her husband was on his fore-feet: which the Fox ſéeing, ſaid to her in a ſcornful manner: Dear Aunt, how much an I bound to you, that takes all this pains for my ſake? queſtionleſſe you ſhall be a ſharer in my Pilgrimage, and taken part in the pardon I ſhall bring from beyond the Seas by the help of your Shoo's. Then <hi>Arſewinde</hi> (though ſpeech were troubleſome to hor) ſaid: Well Sir <hi>Reynard,</hi> you have your will accompliſht; yet heaven (I hope) will requite the miſ-doer. This ſhe ſaid, but her husband and the Bear lay mute, for their wounds were grievous unto them: and ſurely had the Cat been there
<pb facs="tcp:35919:33"/>alſo, he had not eſcap'd ſome extreame puniſhment. The next morning very early, <hi>Reynard</hi> cauſing his ſhooes to be wel oyled, put them on, and made them as fit to his féet, as they were to the Wolvs, and then went to the King and Quéen, and ſaid, My Lord, and Lady, your poor ſubject boweth himſelf before your Majeſties, humbly beſéeching your Highneſſss, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me my male and my ſtaffe bleſt, according to the cuſtome due unto Pilgrims.</p>
               <p>This ſaid, the King ſent for <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ramme, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to ſay ſolemne Maſſe before the Fox, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him his ſtaffe, and his male: but the Ram refuſed ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, My Lord, I dare not, for he hath confeſſed he is in the Popes curſe: and the King ſaid, what of that; have not our Doctors told us, that if a man commit all the ſinnes in the world, yet if he repent himſelf, be ſhriven, do penance, and walke as the Prieſts ſhall inſtruct him, that all is clearely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given him? and hath not <hi>Reynard</hi> done all this? then anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Bellin,</hi> Sir, I am loath to meddle herein, yet if your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie will bear me harmleſſe againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Pren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lor,</hi> (my ordinary) and againſt the Arch-deacon of <hi>Looſ-wind,</hi> and <hi>Rapiamus</hi> his Officiall, I will effect your commandment. At this the King grew angry, and ſaid, I ſcorne to be beholding unto you: but when the Ram ſaw the King offended, hée ſhook for fear, and ran preſently to the Altar; and ſung Maſs, and uſed many ceremonies over the Fox, who gave little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto them, more then the deſire he had to enjoy the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Now when <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ram had finiſhed his Orizons, he preſently hung about <hi>Reynards</hi> neck his male, which was made of the Bears skin, and put into his right foot a Palmers ſtaffe: and thus being furniſhed of all things, he looked ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the King, as if he had been loath to depart; and fained to wéep (though ſorrow and he were never farther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder) onely his worſt grief was, that all in that preſence were not in the ſame caſe that the Bear and the Wolf were, yet he took his leave of them, and deſired every one to pray for him, as he would pray for them: and then offering to depart, (for knowing his own knavery, he was very deſirous to be
<pb facs="tcp:35919:33"/>gone.) The King ſaid, Sir <hi>Reynard,</hi> I am ſorry we muſt part thus ſuddenly: then ſaid the Fox. There is no remedy my Lord, nor ought I be ſlow in ſo devout an action. Then the King took leave, and commanded all that were about him (but the Bear and the Wolf) to attend <hi>Reynard</hi> ſome part of his journey. O he that had ſeen how gallant and perſonable <hi>Reynard</hi> was, and how well his ſtaffe and his male became him: as alſo how fit his ſhoos were for his féet, it could not have choſen but have wirred in him very much laughter: yet the Fox carried himſelf outwardly very demurely: however inwardly he ſmiled at the abuſes he had caſt amongſt them, eſpecially to ſée his enemies, now his attendants, and the King, whom he had moſt palpably wronged with falſe lies, to be aiding to all his vain deſires, did accompany him alſo as if they dad been his commpanions. But the Fox being now on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his way, he ſaid to the King, I beſéech your Majeſty trouble your ſelf no further, but in reſpect of your eaſe, and the danger that might happen to your royall perſon, for you have arreſted two capitall Traitors, who if in your abſence they ſhould get at liberty, the danger were infinite, which might inſue thereon. And this ſaid, he ſtood upon bis hinder féet, and intreated the beſts that were in his company, and would be partakers of his pardon, that they would pray for him: which done, he departed from the King with an excéeding ſad and heavy countenance: Then turning to <hi>Kayward</hi> the Hare, and <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ram, he ſaid with a ſmiling countenance: My beſt friends, ſhall we part thus ſoon? I know your lov's will not leave me yet: with you two I was never offended, and your converſations are agréeable to my nature: for you are mild, loving, and courteous, religious, and full of wiſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, even ſuch as my ſelf was when I was firſt a Recluſe: if you have a few gréen leaves, or a little graſſe, you are well content, as with all the bread and fiſh in the world, and you are temperate and modeſt: and thus with a world of ſuch like flattering words, be inticed theſ two, that they were content to go along with him.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>In the ſpoyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bear of his skin, and the Wolf of his ſhoos, is ſhewed, both the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thinks his Foe weakened enough, till he be utterly rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as alſo the indiſcretion of an over-angry nature, that cannot ſtay to give his wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs aduantage, but utters his ſpleen before he can either get relief or remedy. By the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies done to the Fox, and the curioſity of the Ram, is ſhewed, that in caſes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, (where autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand) for any man to ſtand upon nice and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanicall terms with his ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, doth not onely breed reprehenſion but puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. By the Foxes Hypocriſie, is ſeen the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation of worldly men, and how to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe to the full height, they ever put on a moſt falſe cloke of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. By the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall attendance of all the Beaſts on the Fox, is ſhewed, the flattery and baſeneſſe of many people, that never look how good a man is, but how great, and that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, is ever enough to command at their ſervices.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. 15. How <hi>Kayward</hi> the Hare was ſlain by <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox, and ſent by the Ram to the King</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>All this while ſtood <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ram at the Gate, and grew excéeding angry, both againſt the Fox and the Hare, that they made him waite ſo long: and therefore called out aloud, for <hi>Reynard</hi> to come away: Which when <hi>Reynard</hi> heard, he went forth, and ſaid ſoftly to the Ramme, Good <hi>Bellin</hi> be not offended: <hi>Kyward</hi> is in earneſt conference with his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Aunt, and intreated me to ſay unto you, that if you would be pleaſed te walke before, he would ſpéedily overtake you, for he is light of foot and ſpéedier then you: nor will his Aunt part with him thus ſuddenly, for ſhe and her children are much perplexed at my departure. I but (quoth <hi>Bellin</hi>) me thought I heard <hi>Kyward</hi> cry for help. How, cry for helpe? can you imagine he ſhall receive hurt in my Houſe far be ſuch a thought from you: but I will tell you the reaſon: aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoone as we were come into my houſe, and that <hi>Ermelin</hi> my
<pb facs="tcp:35919:35"/>Wife underſtood of my pilgrimage, preſently ſhe fell downe in a ſwoone: which when <hi>Kyward</hi> ſaw, he cried aloud: O <hi>Bellin</hi> come and help my Aunt, ſhe dies, ſhe dies: then ſaid the Ram, In ſadneſſe I miſtook the cry, and thought the Hare had béen in danger. It was your too much care of him, ſaid the Fox, but before he ſhould have any injury in my houſe, I would leave to reſpect either Wife or Children. But letting this diſcourſe paſſe, you remember <hi>Bellin,</hi> that yeſterday the King and his Councell commanded me, that before I depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Land, I ſhould ſend unto him two Letters, which I have made ready, and will intreat you my deareſt Couſin to bear them to his Majeſtie. The Ram anſwered, I would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly do you the ſervice, if there be nothing but honourable matter contained in your Letters: but I am unprovided of any thing to carry them in. The Fox ſaid, that is provided for you already, for you ſhall have my male, which you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently hang about your neck: I know they will be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully received of his Majeſtie, for they contain matter of great importance. Then <hi>Bellin</hi> promiſed to carry them: So the Fox returned into the houſe, and tooke the male, and put therein the head of <hi>Kyward,</hi> and brought it to the Ram, and gave him a great charge not to looke therein, till it was preſented to the King, as he did expect the Kings favour: and that he might farther indeare himſelfe with his Majeſtie, he bade the Ram take upon him the inditing of the Letters. which will be ſo pleaſing to the King, that queſtionleſſe he will poure upon you many favours.</p>
               <p>The Ram was excéeding glad of his advice, and thanked the Fox, ſaying that the favours he did him ſhould not die unrequited: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd I know it will be much to mine honour, when the King ſhall thinke I am able to indite with ſo great perfection: for I know there be many in theſe daies as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as my ſelfe, that are riſen to high promotion, onely by taking upon them the worth of other mens Labours: And therefore why may not I run the ſame courſe alſo? Yet I pray you <hi>Reynard</hi> farther adviſe me: is it méets that I take <hi>Kyward</hi> the Hare along with me? O by no meanes (ſaid the)
<pb facs="tcp:35919:36"/>Fox) let him come after you, for I know his Aunt will yet not part with him. Beſides, I have other ſecret things to impart to him, which may not yet be revealed. This ſaid, <hi>Bellin</hi> tooke leave of the Fox, and went toward the Court, in which journey he made ſuch ſpeed, that he came thither before noon. where he found the King in his Palace, ſitting amongſt the Nobility.</p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:36"/>
               <figure/>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the killing of the Hare, is ſhewed, that whereas men out of the lightneſſe and eaſineſſe of their belief, do give credit to the entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Adverſaries, or new reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Friends, that evermore ſome inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miſchief doth ſtill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch folly and improvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Alſo how eaſily a malicious man can finde cauſe of quarrel with ſuch as are too weak for them, or as eye-ſores ſtand between them and the end of their purpoſes, or are able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects By the Rams carrying the Hares head to the Lion, and taking upon him to indite the Letters, which he ſaw not: is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuch vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purſes of others qualities, do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver carry their own ſhames and diſreputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and when they look for moſt honour or renown, they reap no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but miſery, ſcorn and diſgrace.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 16. How <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ramme, and his Lineage, were given to the Bear and the Wolfe.</head>
               <p>TO this motion of the Libard the King conſented, ſo that <hi>Firapell</hi> forthwith went to the priſon, where the Bear
<pb facs="tcp:35919:37"/>and the Wolfe were, and ſaid: My Lords, I bring a frée and generall pardon from the King, with his love, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognition of your injuries: which to recompence in ſome large
<figure/> manner out of his Princely bounty, he is pleaſed to beſtow upon you both <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ram, and his whole generation, with
<pb facs="tcp:35919:38"/>whatſoever they poſſeſſe, and is now confiſcate to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, to hold from henceforth, to you and yours, till dooms-day, with full Commiſſion to ſlay, kill and devour them whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you finde them; be it in Woods, Fields or Mountains. And alſo the King granted unto you full power to hunt, kill, or wound <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox whereſoever you finde him, or any of his lineage or generation: and of this great privilege you ſhall receive Lettere Patents at your pleaſure, with onely a reſervation of your fealty and homage to be due to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, which I adviſe you to accept, for it will redound much to your honours. Thus was the peace made between the King and theſe Nobles by the Lybard, and <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ram was forthwith ſlain by them; and all theſe Privileges doth the Woolf hold to this hour, nor could ever any reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be made between them and the Rams kindred. When this peace was thus finiſhed, the King for joy thereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed a Feaſt to be held for twelve daies after, which was done with all ſolemnitie.</p>
               <p>To this feaſt came all manner of wilde Beaſts for it was univerſally known through the whole L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> there wanting any delight or pleaſure that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as muſick, dancing, masking and all Princely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: As for ſeveral meats they were in that abundance, that the Court ſeemed a ſtore-houſe which could not be emptied. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o to this ſeeſt reſorted abundance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ather<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fowl, and all other Creatures that held peace with his Majeſtie, and no one miſſing but the Fox onely. Now after this feaſt has thus continued in all pomp the ſpace of eight daies about high-noon came <hi>Laprell</hi> the Cony before the King and Queen, as they ſate at dinner, and with a heavie and lamentable voice, ſaid; My gracious and great Lord have pitie upon my miſery, and attend my complaint, which is of great violence, force and murther, which <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y have committed againſt me, as I paſſed by the Caſtle of <hi>Malepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> where ſtanding without his gates, attired like a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grime, I ſuppoſing to paſſe peaceably by him toward my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt: hee croſt my way, ſaying his Bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſo devoutly, that I
<pb facs="tcp:35919:38"/>ſaluted him: but he returning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> anſwer, ſtretcht forth his right foot, and gave me ſuch a blow on the neck, betwéen the
<figure/> head and ſhoulders, that I imagined my head had been ſtricken from my body: but yet ſo much memory was left me, that I leapt from his clairs; though moſt grievouſly hurt and
<pb facs="tcp:35919:39"/>wounded. At this he grieved extreamly, becauſe I eſcaped, onely of one of my eares he utterly deprived me; which I beſéech your Majeſty in your royall nature to pitty, and that this bloody murtherer may not live thus to afflict your poor Subjects. Now whil'ſt the Conie was thus ſpeaking to the King, there came flying into the Cout, <hi>Corbant</hi> the Rook, who coming before the King, ſaid: Great King, I beſéech you vouchſafe to hear me, and pitty the complaint I ſhall ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſo it is that I went this morning with <hi>Sharpbeake</hi> my wife, to recreate our ſelves on the Heath, and there we found <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox laid on the ground like a dead carkaſſe, his eyes ſtaring, his tongue lolling out of his mouth, like a dead Hound, ſo that wée wandering at his ſtrange plight, began to féel and touch his body, but found no life therein at all: then went my wife (poor carefull ſoul) and laid her head to his mouth, to ſee if hée drew any breath: which ſhe had no ſooner done; but the foule murtherer awaiting his time, ſnatched her head into his mouth, and bit it quite off. At that I ſcreaked out, and cried: Woe is mée, what misforiunes are theſe? But preſently the murtherer ſtarts up, &amp; reached at me with ſuch a bloody intent, that with much trembling and anguiſh, I was fain to flye up into a trée, where I ſaw him devour up my wife in ſuch terrible manner, that the very thought is death to me in the repeating.</p>
               <p>The maſſacre finiſhed, the murtherer departed, and I went to the place, and gathered the feathers of my loſt wife, which here I humbly preſent before your Majeſty, beſéeching you to do me juſtice, and in ſuch manner to revenge mine injury, that the world may ſpeak fame of your great excellence; for thus to ſuffer your Laws Protections, and ſafe Conducts to be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olated a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> broken, will be ſuch diſreputation and ſcandall to your Crown and Dignity, that your very neighbours and Colleagues, will note and point at your remiſſneſſe: beſides the ſufferance of the evill will make you guilty of the treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which ariſe from ſuch ſufferance: But to your great conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations I leave it: ſince I know your Majeſties own good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will make you carefull of your honour and royalty.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the giving of Bellin unto his enemies, is ſhewed, that when ſimple men give themſelves to pride and vain glory, they are over taken by their enemies, &amp; made ſlaves to ſhame and deſtruction. By the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Conie, is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that when the weak will believe the fair ſhews of the ſtrong and cruell, and ſo commit their ſafeties to their enemies mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom eſcape with life, or if they do by ſome hidden providence, yet it is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever ſome maime, either to their bodies or reputations. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint of the Rook, ſhews, that when the evill man ſleepeth, or ſeemeth to have leaſt power or in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that then his thoughts are moſt buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to deſtroy the innocent, and the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief is more violent, then when he lyeth moſt apparent and publiſheth himſelf an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen enemie; wherefore the ſimple and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent ought at ſuch times to be moſt fearefull, and to keep far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt out of his danger.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. 17. How the King was angry at theſe complaints, took counſel for revenge; and how <hi>Reynard</hi> was forewarned by <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock.</head>
               <p>THe royal King was much moved with anger, when he heard theſe complaints both of the Coney and the Rook; ſo that his eies darting out fire amongſt the beams of Majeſtie, his countenance was dreadful and cruel to look on, and the whole Court trembled to behold him. In the end he ſaid; By my Crown, and the truth I evermore reverence and owe unto the Quéen my Wife, I will ſo revenge theſe outrages committed againſt my Crown and Dignity, that goodneſſe ſhall adore me, and the wicked ſhall die with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance: his falſhood and flatterie ſhall no more get belief in me.</p>
               <p>Is this his journey to <hi>Rome,</hi> and to the <hi>Holy Land?</hi> are theſe the fruits of his Male, his Staffe, and other ornaments be coming a devout Pilgrim? Well, he ſhal find the reward of his Treaſons: but it was not my belief, but the perſwaſion of my Quéen; nor am I the firſt that hath been deceived by that ſoft gender, ſince many great ſpirits have fallen through their inticements. And this ſaid, he commanded all that were about him, both Noble, worthy, and every diſcréet ſpirit to aſſiſt him with their counſel, and to lay him down ſuch ſure ground for his revenge, that his honour and royaltie might be anew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, and every offender made to know and féel the heavie price for their moſt unjuſt actions.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>To this ſpéech <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf replied; Sir <hi>Firapel,</hi> for my own part, I think not any of this aſſemblie will diſſent from your counſel, ſo it may ſtand with the pleaſure of my Lord the King: yet this I dare maintein, that howſoever <hi>Reynard</hi> ſhall clear himſelf of theſe, and a thouſand ſuch like treſpaſſes which ſhall be brought againſt him: Yet I have that lodgeth in my boſome, which ſhall approve he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited his life: but at this time his abſence ſhall make me ſilent, onely touching the treaſure of which he hath informed his Majeſtie to lie at <hi>Crekenpit</hi> in <hi>Huſterloe,</hi> there never came a falſer information from the mouth of any creature: for it was a lie made out of malice to wrong me and the Bear, and get himſelf libertie to rob and ſpoil all that paſſe by his houſe, as now he doth: but not withſtanding I held it meet that all things be done as ſhall ſeem god to his majeſtie, or you Sir <hi>Firapel:</hi> Yet this believe, that if he had meant to have appeared he had béen here long ſince for he had ſummons given him by the Kings Meſſenger.</p>
               <p>To this the King anſwered, I will have no other courſe of ſummoning him, but command all that owe me allegiance or reſpect mine honour, that forthwith they make themſelves
<pb facs="tcp:35919:41"/>ready for the war: and at the end of ſix daies appear before me with their Bowes, Gunns, Bumbards, Pikes and Halberds; ſome on horſe-back, ſome on foot, for I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege <hi>Malepardus</hi> inſtantly, and deſtroy <hi>Reynard</hi> and his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration from the earth for ever: this if any diſlike, let him turn his back, that I may know him for mine enemie. And they all cried with one voice, we are ready to attend your Majeſtie. When <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock heard this determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he grew excéeding ſorry (though his ſorrow was deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate) and ſtealing from the reſt of the company, hee ran with all ſpeed poſſible to <hi>Mallepardus,</hi> neither ſparing buſh nor brier, pale nor rail: and as he went, he ſaid to himſelf; Alas my dear Vncle <hi>Reynard!</hi> into what hazards art thou drawn, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing but one ſtep betwixt thée and thy death, or at the beſt, thine everlaſting baniſhment? Well may I grieve for thée, ſince thou art the top and honour of my houſe, art wiſe and politick, and a friend to thy friends when they ſtand in need of thy counſel; for with thy ſwéet language thou canſt inchant all creatures, but all is now bootleſſe. With ſuch manner of lamentations as theſe, came <hi>Grimbard</hi> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to <hi>Mallepardus,</hi> and found his Vncle <hi>Reynard</hi> ſtanding at the Caſtle gates, who had newly gotten two young Pigeons as they came créeping out of their neſt, to try how they could learn to flie. But now beholding his Nephew <hi>Grimbard,</hi> he ſtaid, and ſaid, Welcome my beſt beloved Nephew, the onely hee I eſteem above all my kindred: Surely you have run exceeding faſt, for you ſweat wonderfully: What newes man, how runs the ſquares at the Court? O ſaid <hi>Grimbard,</hi> exceeding ill with you; for you have forfeited both your life, honour, and eſtate. The King is up in armes againſt you with horſe-men, and foot-men, and ſouldiers innumerable: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Iſegrim</hi> and <hi>Bruine</hi> are now in more favour with his Majeſtie, then I am with you; therefore it is high time you have great care of your ſelf, for their envie hath toucht you to the quick; they have informed againſt you, that you are a thief and a murtherer: and to ſecond their informations. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prel</hi> the Coney, and <hi>Corbant</hi> the Rook have made hainous
<pb facs="tcp:35919:41"/>complaints againſt you, ſo that but your ſhamefull death, I ſée no eſcape or freedome.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Tuſh (ſaid the Fox) my dear Nephew, if this be the worſt, let no ſorrow affright you: but let us be chéerfull and pleaſant together, for though the King and all the Court
<pb facs="tcp:35919:42"/>would ſwear my death, yet will I be exalted above them all, well may they prate and jangle, and tire themſelves with their counſells, but without the help of my wit and policie, neither can the Cour or Common-wealth have any long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. Come then my beſt Nephew, let us enter into my Caſtle and feaſt, I have a pair of fat Pigeons for you, which are meat of pure and light digeſtion; I love not any thing better, they are young and tender, and may be almoſt ſwallower whole, for their bones are little other then blood; yet come I ſay, my wife <hi>Ermeline</hi> will receive you kindly, but by all meanes report not to her of any dangers, for ſhe is of ſoft and melting temper, and it might ſtrike her into ſuddain ſickneſs, for women are apt to entertain grief. When wée have feaſted, I will then to morrow early in the morning go with you to the Court, and if I can but attain ſpeech with the King, I ſhall gall ſome deep enough, onely this I deſire (dear Nephew) at your hands, that you will ſtand to me, as one friend and kinſman ought to do one by another. Doubt me not (ſaid <hi>Grimbard</hi>) for both my life and goods ſhal be at your ſervice. I thank you Nephew (ſaid the Fox) and you ſhall not find me ingratefull. Sir (ſaid the Brock) be bold of this, that you ſhall come and make your anſwer before the Lords fréely, for none ſhall dare to arreſt or hold you, for that favour the Quéen and the Libard have purchaſt from the King. I am glad of that (ſaid the Fox) nor eate I then a hair for their worſt malice. And this ſaid, they went into <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardus,</hi> and found <hi>Ermelin</hi> ſitting amongſt her younglings, who preſently aroſe, and received the Brock with all reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and he on the other part ſaluted her and her chidren with all courteſie. Preſently the two Piegons were made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and they ſupped together, each taking their part though none had ſo much as they deſired: then ſaid the Fox, Nephew, how like you my children <hi>Roſſel</hi> and <hi>Reynardine?</hi> I hope they will do honour to our family, they are towardly I aſſure you, for the one lately caught Chicken, and the other hath killed a Pullet: they are alſo good Duckers, and can both deceiv the Lapwing and the Mallard: I tell you true, I dare already
<pb facs="tcp:35919:42"/>adventure them farre, onely I mean firſt to inſtruct them how to eſcape the Grins, and to prevent both the Huntſman and his Hounds; they are of the right heir Nephew, and like me, both in countenance and quality; they play grinning, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle ſoothing, and kill ſmiling: this is the true nature of the Fox, and in this they are perfect, which is great pride unto me.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>The anger of the Lion at the Foxes treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, ſhews the diſpoſition of a good Prince; which is ever moved and offended, when his good ſubjects are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured. And the perſwaſion of the Queen and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard, ſhews, the true tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance which every Prince ſhould uſe when he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtreth Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. The mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, yet biting words of the Wolf, ſhews, the cunning malice of a ſubtil foe, who before ſuch as are of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary faction, will conceal the violence of his malice: that ſo he may gain a more quiet attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then mixing his calme words with bitte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bitter promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and doubt full injuries, doth the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt he can to poiſon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion of him be hateth. The Brocks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oing to the Fox, ſheweth the office of a true friend, which bo h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>veth warning and advice to them they love, when the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſee them run into evil courſes. The Foxes careleſneſſe ſhews the true nature of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate man; that when he hath plunged himſelf into the depth of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an audacious countenance and an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſhew, to make him ſeem innocent, yet evermore his heart is nip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with the ſtinging of his coſcience, as o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> as he is alone, which is the torment of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very offender.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 18 How the Fox repenting his ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, doth make his confeſſion, and is abſolved by the Brock.</head>
               <p>UNCLE, ſaid the Brock, you may be proud that you have ſuch toward children: and rejoice becauſe they are of my blood. I thank you Nephew, (ſaid the Fox) but I know your journey hath made you weary, therefore you ſhall go to your reſt: to which the Brock conſented, ſo they laid them down upon ſtraw litter, and all ſlept ſoundly, but the Fox, whoſe heart was heavy with ſorrow, lay ſtudying, how he might beſt excuſe himſelf before the King. But as ſoon as the morning began to riſe from the top of the Mountaines he aroſe, and went with <hi>Grimbard</hi> towards the Court; yet before he went, he took leave of his wife and children; and ſaid, Think not mine abſence long; (dear wife and children) for I muſt go to the Court with my Couſin <hi>Grimbart,</hi> and though my ſtay be more then ordinary, yet take no affright thereat; and what tidings ſoever you hear, yet conſider all things for the beſt; and be carefull of your ſelves, and keep my Caſtle cloſe, and well guarded: as for my ſelf doubt not but I will defeat all mine enemies. Alas <hi>Reynard</hi> (ſeid his wife) what moves you to take this ſuddain journey? the laſt time you were at the Court, you know what daggers you eſcaped; and you vowed never to ſée it again. Will you now run a ſecond hazard? Dame (ſaid the Fox) the occurrants of the world are divers and uncertain; and we are ſubject to the ſtrokes of fortune: but reſt you content, there is neceſſity that I go, and I hope my ſtay ſhall not be above five <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35919:43"/>at the uttermoſt, and ſo imbracing his wife &amp; children, he took leave and departed: and as they journied over the Heath, <hi>Reynard</hi> ſaid to the Brock: Nephew, ſince I was laſt ſhri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, I have committed many ſins, therefore I beſéech you let me make before you my confeſſion, that I may paſſe with leſſe trouble through my worſt dangers.</p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:43"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>As I went talking with the Wolf between <hi>Houthluſt,</hi> and <hi>Elverding,</hi> wée beheld a goodly Bay Mare graſing, with a black Fole by her ſide; which was exceeding fat and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: the Wolf at that inſtant was almoſt dead for hunger, in ſo much that he intreated mée to go to the Mare, and know if ſhe would ſell her fole? I went and demanded the queſtion. The Mare ſaid, ſhe would willingly ſell it for Money: I then asked the price? and ſhe ſaid, the price was written in her hinder foot, which if I pleaſed I might come and read it at my pleaſure; but I that well underſtood her politick anger, ſaid, It is truth that I cannot read, neither do I deſire to buy your Fole, onely I am a meſſenger from the Wolf, who hath a great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſire to have it. Then (ſaid the Mare) let him come himſelf; and I will give him ſatisfaction: Then went I to the Wolf, and told him what the Mare ſaid; aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him, that if he pleaſed he might have his belly full of the Fole: provided he could read, for the price was written in the Mares hinder foot. Read (ſaid the Wolf) what ſhould a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e me; I can, Couſin read, both Latine, French, Engliſh, and Dutch, I have ſtudyed in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and argued with many Doctors; I have heard many ſtately Plays, and ſitten in the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace of Iudgement: I have taken degrees in both the Laws; nor is there that writing which I cannot diſcipher: So deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me to ſtay for him there; away he went to the Mare, and craved that he might ſée and read the price of the Fole: to which the Mare conſented and lifting up her hinder foot, which was newly ſhod with ſtrong iron, and ſeven ſharp naile-heads, as the Wolf look'd thereon, ſhe ſmote him ſo juſt upon the fore-head, that ſhe threw him over and over, and he lay in a dead ſound whil'ſt a man might have ridden a mile and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; which don, away trotted the Mare with her Colt,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:44"/>and left the poor Wolf bloody and wounded, in ſo much that he howled like a Dog: then went I to him, and ſaid Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> dear Vncle, how do you, have you eaten too much of the Colt? indeed you are unkind, that will give mee no part with you. I went your meſſage honeſtly; me thinks you have out ſlept your dinner: good Vncle tell me what was written under the Mares foot, was it in Proſe or Rime? in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I would fain know it: I think it was a Prick-ſong, for I heard you ſing? nay, you ſhew your ſcholer-ſhip in all the Arts.</p>
               <p>Alas, <hi>Reynard,</hi> (alas ſaid the Wolf) I pray you forbeare to diſdain me, for I am extreamly wounded, and mine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh is ſo great, that a heart of flint would pitty me; The damned Mare on her long legge hath an iron foot, and I took the nails to have been Letters, on which I looked: ſhe hit me ſo full on the head, I think my ſcull is cloven. Dear Vncle (ſaid the Fox) is this truth which you tell me? believe it, you make me wonder, why I took you for one of the greateſt Clarks in this Kingdom: Well, I perceive the old Proverb is now made good in you: <hi>The greateſt Clarks are not the wiſeſt men.</hi> Poor men ſomtimes may out-ſtrip them in Iudgment; and the reaſon is, you great Schollers, ſtudy ſo much, that you grow dull, in that you ſo much over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labour. And thus with theſe mocks and taunts, I brought the Wolf within a haires breadth to deſtruction. And now fair Nephew. I have unladed my Conſcience, and delivered as many of my ſins as I can call to remembrance; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you let me receive abſolution and penance: and then come what cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce ſhall at the Court, I am armed againſt all dangers. Then <hi>Grimbard</hi> ſaid, your treſpaſſes are great and heinous, neverheleſſe who is dead, muſt abide dead. And therefore here I freely abſolve you, upon aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of your hearty repentance: onely the contempt you made in ſending him <hi>Kywards</hi> head, and the abuſe of ſo many falſhoods, will lye heavy upon you. Why (ſaid the Fox) he that will live in the world to ſee this, or hear that, and underſtand the third, muſt ever converſe with affliction.
<pb facs="tcp:35919:45"/>No man can touch Honey, but he muſt lick his fingers. I often féel touches of repentance, but reaſon and our will, are ever in continual combate; ſo that I oft ſtand ſtill, as at my wits end: and cry out againſt my ſins, féeling a deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. But preſently the world and her vanities ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to me again: and when I find ſo many ſtones and rubs in my way, and the examples of the crafty Prelates, and rich Prieſts to inchaunt me, that I am forthwith taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? the world fills me with covetouſneſe, and the fleſh with wantonneſs; ſo that looſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing my good reſolutions. I am onely for Hell and wickedneſs. I hear their ſinging, piping, laughing, playing, and all kind of mirth; and I ſee their words and actions ſo contrary, that nothing is more uncertain and various: from them I learn my lying, and from Lords Courts my flattery: for certainly Lords, Ladies, Prieſts, and Clerkes, uſe moſt diſſimulation. It is now an offence to tell great men truth: and he that cannot diſſemble, cannot live. I have oft heard men ſpeak truth, yet they have ſtill grac'd it with falſhood: for untruths many times happen into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe unwillingly and without knowledge: yet having a handſome garment, it ever goes for currant. (Dear Nephew) it is now a faſhion to lye, flatter, ſooth, threaten, pray and curſe, and to do any thing that may kéep the weak in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; who do otherwiſe is held fooliſh: but he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wimble falſhood, in truths kerchiefe, hath neither Art nor cunning: but he that can do it, and deliver errour without ſtammering, he may do wonders; he may we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Scarlet. Gray or Purple: he ſhall gain both by the Laws ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and temporall, and write himſelf conquerour in every deſignment. There be many that imagine they can i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neatly: but their cunning oft failes them: ſo that when they think to féed of the fat morſells, they ſlip quite beſides their tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. Others blunt and fooliſh, and for want of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod marre all their diſcourſes, but he that can give to his lie a fit and an apt concluſion, can pronounce it without rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and make it as truth, fair and amiable: That is the man, and worthy of nomiration. But to ſpeak truth is
<pb facs="tcp:35919:45"/>no cunning, it never makes the Devill laugh: foly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> well and with a grace: to lift up wrong above right, to make mountains and build Caſtles in the aire: to make men juggle and look thorow their fingers, and all for hope of gain onely. This Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, is an Art beyond expreſſion; yet evermore of the end cometh miſery and affliction. I will not deny but ſomtimes men may jeſt or lye in ſmall things, for he that will ſpeak all truths, ſhall ſomtimes ſpeak out of ſeaſon. To play <hi>Place<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo,</hi> may now and the be born with; for who ſo ſpeaks all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways truth, ſhall finde many rubs in his way: men may erre for néed, and mend it by counſell, ſince no treſpaſs but hath his mercy: nor any wiſdom but at ſomtime dulleth. Then (ſaid the Brock) Vncle; you are ſo wiſe you cannot fail in any purpoſe, and I would grow inamored of you; your reaſons ſo far ſurpaſs my underſtanding, that it is no néed of your ſhrift; for your ſelf may both play the Prieſt and confeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or: you know the world in ſuch ſort, that it is impoſſible for any man to halt before you.</p>
               <p>With theſe and ſuch manner of diſcourſes, they held on their journey towards the Court: yet the Foxes heart (for all his fair ſhew) was ſad and heavy; yet countenance bewrai'd it not: but he paſt without amazement through all the preſs of the Court, even till he came to the preſence of the King, and the Brock march'd cloſe by his ſide; ſaying, Vncle, be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, but be of good chéer, it is courage of whom Fortune is ever enamoured Then (ſaid the Fox) Nephew, you ſay true, and your comfort avails me: and ſo on he went caſting many diſdainful countenances on thoſe he lik'd not; or as who would ſay, Here I am: what is it that the proudeſt of yon dare object againſt me? he beheld there many of his kin which hée knew loved him not, as the <hi>Otter,</hi> the <hi>Bever,</hi> and divers others which I will name hereafter: and many he ſaw which loved him. As ſoon as he was come in the view of the King, he fell down humbly on his knée, and ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>The Foxes ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ving him ſelf to the Brock, ſhewes the Art of all diſemblers, which ever make devotion their cloak. By h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>buying of the Foal of the Mare, is ſhewed, that when proud men make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of wiſer then themſelves, &amp; ſuch as affect not their qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lities, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they do them is ever to bring them to miſchief, &amp;c Alſo when am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs blinds men, and makes them truſt onely in their own skill and knowledge, that then they are ever ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ainly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with one miſchief or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and made a mock and ſcorn to their foes, and ſuch as led them blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold into the evill.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:46"/>
               <head>CHAP. 9. How <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox excuſed himſelf before the King, and of the Kings anſwer.</head>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p>Then ſaid the Ape, Couſin, caſt off your ſorrow for I know the way to <hi>Rome</hi> wel and am experienced in theſe buſineſſes for I am called the Biſhops Clerke, therefore I will go thither, and enter a plea againſt the Archdeacon, and in ſpight of his will bring you from the Pope a will ſeel'd abſolution.</p>
               <p>But, man I have many great friends there as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Vncle <hi>Sim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and others, <hi>Pren tour, Wai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                        <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and the like, all which will ſtand unto me: beſides I will not go unfurniſhed of money, for I know Paratersare beſt heard with gift; and the Law hath no feet to walke on but money: a true friend in tried in neceſſity, and you ſhall finde me without diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: therefore caſt off your griefe, and go to the Court as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for I will preſently to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and in the mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e time, here I quit you of all your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nues and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſences and an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t them upon my ſelfe: when you come to the
<pb facs="tcp:35919:50"/>Court you ſhall finde there Dame <hi>Rukenaw</hi> my wife, her two ſiſters, and my three children, with divers others of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. I pray you ſalute them from me, and ſhew them mine occaſions: my wife is excéeding wife, and ſhe ſhall finde that her diſtreſſed freinds ſhall not ſhrinke when I can help them I know ſhe is faithfull and as behoves her, will never leave her friend in danger. At the uttermoſt If your oppreſſion be more then you can beare, ſend preſently to me to <hi>Rome,</hi> and not an enemy that you have, be it King or Queene, or Sub, ject even from the higheſt to the loweſt, but I will preſently put them in the Popes curſe, and ſend back ſuch an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, that no holy or ſacred duty ſhall be performed till you have right and Iuſtice reſtored you.</p>
               <p>This aſſure your ſelfe I can eaſily performe, for his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is very old, and little regarded; onely now Cardinall <hi>Pare-gold</hi> beareth all the ſway in the Country, as being young, and rich in many friends: beſides, he hath a Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine: of whome he is farre enamoured: that he denies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhe demandeth: his Lady is my Niece, and will doe whatſoever I requeſt her: therefore Couſin, goe boldly to the King, and charge him to do you Iuſtice, which I know hee will, ſince he underſtands the Lawes are made for the uſe of all men.</p>
               <p>This (my Soveraigne Lord the King) when I heard him ſpeak, I ſmil'd, and with great joy came hither to relate unto you the truth? that can charge me with any Creature within this Court, that can charge me with any treſpaſs whatſoever, and prove it by teſtimony, as the Law requireth, or if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, he will oppoſe himſelfe againſt me, perſon to perſon, grant me but a day, and equall liſts, and in combate I will maintaine my innocency againſt him: provided he be equal to me in birth and degree: this Law hath ever hitherto ſtood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and I hope neither in me, for me, or by me, it ſhal now be broken.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolfe, and <hi>Bruine</hi> the Beare, were very sad when they ſaw theſe two forſake the Court: whereupon the King ſaid, If any will appeale the Fox, let him come forth, and he ſhall be heard: Yeſterday wee were laden with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plants, where are they to day? Here is the Fox ready to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Then ſaid the Fox, My ſoveraign Lord, abſence makes impudent accuſers bold, when preſence dants them, as your Highneſs may ſée both by the Coney and the Rooke: O what it is to truſt the malice of theſe Towards! and how ſoon they may confound good men: but for me it matters not: nevertheleſs had they (at your Majeſties commandment) but askt me forgiveneſs, I had quickly caſt all their offences
<pb facs="tcp:35919:51"/>behind mée, for I will never ſhake hands with charitie, nor ever hate or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> mine enemies: my revence I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to heaven, and Iuſtice by your Majeſtie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid the King <hi>Reynard.</hi> you ſpeake well i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the inwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart be like the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew, yet I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> your griefe is not ſuch as you expreſſe it: It far ſurmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is it ſaid the Fox: No quoth the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you with one foule treaſon, which is, when I had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> your great tranſgreſſions and you had promiſed me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pilgrimage to the holy Lord: when I had furniſhed you with male, with ſtaffe, and all things fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that holy order, then in the greateſt deſpite you ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t me back in the male by <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ram the head of <hi>Reynard</hi> the Hare, a thing ſo nowriouſly to my diſgrace and diſhonour, that no treaſon can be fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer. This you have no colour to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for <hi>Bellin</hi> (our Chaplain) at his death revealed the whole proceſſe, and the ſame reward which he then gained, the ſame you ſhall receive, or elſe right ſhall fail mée.</p>
               <p>At this ſentence <hi>Reynard</hi> grew ſo fore afraid, that he knew not what to ſay, but looked with a pitifull countenance upon all his kindred which ſtood round about him; his colour went and came, and his heart fainted, but none ſent him either hand or foot to helpe him: then the King ſaid, Thou diſſembling and falſe T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aytor, why art thou now ſo dumbe, But the Fox being full of anguiſh, fetch a ſigh as if his heart would have broke; ſo that every beaſt pitied him, ſave onely the Bear and the Wolf, which rejoiced to ſee his ſorrow.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>The boldneſſe of the Foxes apperance and ſpeech, ſhewes the impudence of a deſperate offender, that having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his owne boldnes to bolſter out his cauſe, ſtill cries for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring not ſo much to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelfe, as to accuſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and by digreſſions &amp; extravagant ſpeech to bring all thoſe into diſgrace which are able to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie any thing againſt him. By the tale of the Apes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him to Rome, and his threatning the King, is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſottiſh blindneſſe of the old times, which would thrall Kings under the Popes Curſe, and make them ſubject to his Commands, though they were never ſo heathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh and Diabolicall. By his excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him of the crimes againſt the Coney and the Rooke, is ſhewed, that whoſoevers is reſolved to do an ill act, will never make conſcience to tell a loud Lie; nor is he ever uprovided thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which he ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hes his knavery with. <hi>By</hi> the Apes friend is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> or Simau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> or <hi>take ill,</hi> and <hi>Wait S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ath</hi> or <hi>do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſcheife,</hi> is ſhewed the wickedneſſe of theſe days in Rome, and how by much mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es a man might purchaſe any thing he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t about. By his inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the Apes wiſe (who was then a great favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> about the Queene) is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſubtill head, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> himſelfe among party, will not ſpare any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ar ones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are not the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erior open their lips. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y the slight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Core<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſoon the weak are terrified &amp; danted with the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the strong and mighty, that it is better to ſit down with wrong, then to contend with one that hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth too ſtrong a party. And alſo how by ſuch advantage the offender takes heart, &amp; thereon grounds the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trength of his greater inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. By the Lyon, laſt accuſations and the Foxes direction, is ſhewed, that when truth &amp; authority ſtand up againſt the wicked, that then studying with his owne conſcience, he is able to abide no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilence and downe caſt look, he ſhews plainly the guile which lies within him.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 20. How Dame <hi>Rukenaw</hi> anſwered for the Fox to the King, and of the Parable ſhe told him.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>To this ſpeech the King made his anſwer: Dame, had the Fox done that offence to you he hath done to others, your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe would couch in another nature, you cannot blame me to
<pb facs="tcp:35919:52"/>hate him, ſince it is onely he which breaketh my laws &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants? you have heard him accuſed of theft, murther and treaſon, how can you then defend him? if you will néeds make him your Saint, then ſet him upon the Altar, and do him wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but believe it, there is no one good thing in him: and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you imagine, yet ſearch him, and you ſhall find him rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and deformed, there is neither kinſman nor friend (but your ſelf) that will aſſiſt him, and therefore your violence draws my greater wonder. What companion hath he that ever thrived by his ſociety, or whom hath he ſmil'd on, that his tail hath not after daſht out the eie of.</p>
               <p>To this the ſhe-Ape replied: My Lord, I love him, and have ever born him a ſingular reverence, and I can well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count one noble and good action he did in your preſence: for which then you thanked him, though now forgotten: yet the heavieſt thing ſhould ever weigh the moſt, and men ſhould kéep a meaſure in their affections, and not hate, nor love with violence; ſince conſtancie is the greateſt ornament of a Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nature. We ſhould not praiſe the day til the evening come, nor is good counſel availeable, but to thoſe which mean to purſue it.</p>
               <p>I remember about ſome two years ſince, there came to this court a man and a ſerpent to have judgment in a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful controverſie: For the Serpent attempting to go through a he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g, was taken by the neck with a ſnare ſo that there was no way to eſcape with life: A certain man paſſing by, the Serpent called and cried unto him, and deſired his help, or elſe he ſhould periſh preſently. The man taking pitie of him (ſaid) If thou wilt faithfully promiſe me neither to do mee hurt with thy tooth or tail, or other poiſon about thée, I will releaſe thee. The Serpent preſently ſwore he would not, neither at that time, nor any time hereafter: ſo the man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſed him, and ſet him free, and they went forth and travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together a long ſeaſon.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>The Serpent agreed thereto; ſo they travelled till they met
<pb facs="tcp:35919:53"/>with <hi>Tiſellin</hi> the Raven, and <hi>Slinopere</hi> his ſonne: to whom relating the difference, the Raven adjudged that the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſhould eat the man, hoping that he and his ſon ſhould get a ſhare alſo. But the man ſaid, How ſhall he that is a robber, and lives by blood, judge this cauſe? it muſt not be one but divers, and ſuch as know both Law and equity, that muſt judge this contention: the Raven is neither juſt, nor indifferent.</p>
               <p>Then they travelled till they met the Bear and the Wolfe, unto whom alſo they told the matter, and they adjudged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the man likewiſe. Then the Serpent began to caſt his venom, at the man, but the man leaped away, and ſaid, You do me wrong, thus to attempt to kill me: and the Serpent ſaid, Hath not Iudgment gone twice on my ſide? Yes (ſaid the Man) by ſuch as are murtherers themſelves, and ſuch as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver kept promiſe: but I appeale to the Court, let mee be tryed by your King, and what judgment he giveth, I will willingly abide. To this all conſented: So they came to the Court before your Majeſty, and the Wolfes two children came with their Father, the one was call <hi>Empty-Belly,</hi> the other <hi>Navel-full,</hi> becauſe they ſought to devour the Man. So the full proceſſe of the matter was declared to your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie: But the Mans kindneſſe and covenant, the Serpents danger and Faith-breach, occaſioned through the extremitie of hunger. Remember how much your Highnes was perplexed with their difference, and all your Counſell alſo: For the Mans ſorrow, the Serpents hunger: the Mans good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and the Serpents ingratitude, equally raiſeth much pitty in your boſome. But in the end ſuch doubts roſe, that not any in your Court was able to judge it. At the laſt, when no helpe could be found, then you commanded my kinſman <hi>Reynard</hi> to decide the buſineſſe: the a was he Oracle of the Court, nor was any thing received, but what he propounded: But he told your Maieſty it was impoſſïble to give true Iudgment according to their relations, but if he might ſée the Serpent in what manner he was fettered, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his danger, then he knew wel how to give Iudgment
<pb facs="tcp:35919:54"/>therein. Then you commended him, and called him by the the title of Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> aproving that to be done which he had ſpoken.</p>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p>Then ſaid the Queen to <hi>Rukenaw:</hi> Thus much I told into his Majeſtie yeſterday, but his anger was ſo great, hee would not give ear to me. Alſo the Libero ſaid, Sir, you muſt iudge according to witneſs: for to be governed by will is tyrannous and ignoble. Then a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſwered the King, It is true you inform me? but the diſgrace done to my particular ſelf in <hi>Kywards</hi> death, and others informations robb'd me of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that I had no leiſure to look back either to Law, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Therefore now let the Fox ſpeak bold'y, and if he can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtly acquit himſelf of the crime laid againſt him, I ſhall gladly reſtore him his liberty, and the rather for you his dear friends ſake, whom I have ever found faithful and loyal.</p>
               <p>O how infinitely glad was the Fox when hée heard th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe words, and ſaid in himſelf, Thanks my noble Aunt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, thou haſt put me new bloſſoms on my dry'd Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſet me in a fair path to libertie. I have one good f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t to dance on: and I doubt not but to uſe my Art of di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo bravely, that this day ſhall be remembred for my renown and victory.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the ſhee Apes anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Fox, is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how apt weak women are to be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into any beliefs, in which they may either expreſſe their pitty, or gain glory. Alſo it ſhews the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the old proverb, That a Friend in Court is ever w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rth a pound in a mans pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe. By the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of her defence, is ſhewed, the true nature of a woman that evermore turns into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames, and ſo ſhee may doe the good or evill ſhe in tends, will not keep any thing concealed with may any way work for her purpoſe, nor yet any thing unurged which may diſgrace thoſe that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the contrary facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of the Man and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, in which ſhe ſheweth the wiſedom of the Fox, and the folly and diſability of the Bear, the Wolf and the reſt of the Foxes ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:56"/>
               <head>CHAP. 21. How <hi>Reynard</hi> excuſed himſelf of <hi>Kaywards</hi> death, and all other imputations; got the Kings favour, and made relation of certain Jewels.</head>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p>This combe is poliſhed like unto fine ſilver, and the téeth of it be ſmal and ſtreight, and between the great teeth and the ſmall, in a large field or ſpace, there is graven many an Image ſubtilly made, and eunningly enamelled about with fine gold: the field is checked with Sables and Silver, and enamelled with Eybor and Azure: and therein is contained the ſtory how <hi>Venus, Juno,</hi> and <hi>Pallas</hi> ſtrove for the golden Ball in the mountain <hi>Ida,</hi> and how it was put to <hi>Paris,</hi> to give it to the faireſt of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paris</hi> at that time was a Shpherd, and kept his Flocks
<pb facs="tcp:35919:58"/>with <hi>Oenon</hi> on that hill, and as ſoon as he had receiv'd the Ball, <hi>Juno</hi> promis'd, if he would beſtow it on her ſhe would make him the richeſt man in the world. <hi>Pallas</hi> ſaid, That ſhe might have it, to make him the wiſeſt man in the world, and the moſt fortunate againſt his enemies. But when <hi>Venus</hi> ſaid, What needſt thou wealth, wiſdom or valour? Art thou not <hi>Priamus</hi> ſon, and <hi>Hectors</hi> brother, which have all <hi>Afia</hi> under their power? Art thou not one of the heirs of mighty <hi>Troy?</hi> come give me the Ball, and I will give thee the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt treaſure of the world, and that ſhall be the faireſt Lady breathing; ſhe, whoſe like no Sun ſhall ever again behold: ſo ſhalt thou be richer then riches, and climbe above all in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: that's the wealth none can praiſe too much, ſince beauty is that heavenly Elixar, which turns all things in man to joy and contentment.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Paris</hi> heard this, he deſired to know the Ladie; and <hi>Venus</hi> ſaid, It is <hi>Hellen</hi> of <hi>Greece,</hi> the wife of King <hi>Mene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus;</hi> ſhe that is the Iem of the world, the treaſure of beauty, and the glory of all eies which did be hold her: then preſently <hi>Paris</hi> gave her the Ball, and confirm'd her fairer then the other Goddeſſes. Then another place was figured how he won <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> brougt her to <hi>Troy,</hi> the ſolemnitie at the marriage, the honour at the triumphs, and all things elſe contein'd in that large ſtory.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figure/>
               </figure>
               <p>Of this wood the Glaſſe-caſe was made, being larger then the Glaſſe by half a foot and more ſquare, upon which verge was decyphred divers many ſtrange Hiſtories, in Gold, in Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in Sables, Yellow, Azure and Cynope: and theſe colours were very curiouſly wrought and interlaid together, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der each Hiſtory the words ſo engraven and enamelled, that any man might read the whole Story: believe it, the world never produced a thing of a greater worth, luſtre, or pleaſure. In the upper part thereof ſtood a Horſe in his naturall glory, fat, fair, and fiery, which braved a ſtately Hart which ran before him: but ſéeing he could not overtake this Hart in ſwiftneſs, at which he infinitely diſoained, he went to a Heardſman ſtanding by, and told him, if he would help him to take a Hart which he would ſhew him, he ſhould have all the profit of the conqueſt, as the hornes, skin, and fleſh: Then the Heardſman asked him what meanes he ſhould uſe to get him: the Horſe ſaid, mount upon my back, and I will bear thée after him, till with tyring we take him. The heardſman took his offer, and beſtriding the Horſe, followed the Dear: but he fled away ſo faſt, and got ſo much ground of the Horſe, that with much labour the Horſe grew weary, and he bade the Heardſman light, for he would reſt himſelf awhile. But the Heardſman ſaid; I have a bridle on thy head, and ſpurrs on my héebs, therefore know thou art now my ſervant, neither will I part with thée, but govern thée as ſéems beſt to my pleaſure. Thus the Horſe brought himſelf into thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and was taken in his own net for no creature
<pb facs="tcp:35919:60"/>hath a greater adverſary then his own envy, and many which labour the hart of others ſtill fall upon their own ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines.</p>
               <p>In another part was figured an Aſſe and an Hound, which were both the ſervants of a rich man. This man loved his Hound exceedingly, and would oft play with him, and ſuffer the dog to faun and leap upon him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow and then to lick him about the mouth. Now when <hi>Baeldwin</hi> the Aſſe ſaw this, he began to envy the Hound, and ſaid, Whet ſees my Maſter in this foul Houmd, that he ſuffers him thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to leap upon him, and kiſſe him? I ſée no profitable ſervice he doth him. I labour, bear and draw, and do more ſervice in one wéek, then the dog and his whole kind are able to do in a year, and yet have I not the tythe of his favours: for hée ſitteth by his trencher, eats the fat of his meat, and lies on Carpets and pillows: when I that do all, am fed onely with Netties and Thiſtles: well I will no longer indure it, but I will ſtudy to have my Lords favour as much as the Hound if not in greater meaſure. Anon the Maſter of the houſe came home; and the Aſſe lifting up his tail, leapt with his fore-féet on his ſhoulders, and braying and grinning, and put forth his mouth to kiſſe him, and uſed ſuch rude unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly actions, that he rub'd all the skin from his Maſters eares, and almoſt overthrew him: ſo that the man was forced to cry out help, help, for this Aſſs will kill me. Then came in his ſervants with ſtaves, and beat the Aſſe ſo excéedingly, that he was almoſt ſlain: which dore, he returned to his ſtall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: and was an Aſſe as he was before. In the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they which do envy and ſpight at others welfare, if they receive the ſame reward, it is nothing more then is due to their merit: for an Aſſe is an Aſſe, and was born to eat Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: and where Aſſes govern, there order is never obſerved, for they have no eye either on this ſide, or beyond their own private profit: yet ſometimes they are advanced, the more is the pitty.</p>
               <p>In another part was figured the Story, how my Father and <hi>Tybert</hi> the Cat travailed together, and had ſworn by their
<pb facs="tcp:35919:60"/>troath, that neither for love nor hate they would depart one from the other: but it happened on a time, they ſaw Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters coming over the fields with a Kennell of Hounds, from which they ſled apace, for their lives were in danger, Then ſaid the Fox, <hi>Tybert,</hi> whither ſhall we flie: for the Hunters have eſpied us? for mine own part I have a thouſand wiles to eſcape them, and as long as we abide together, we ſhall not néed to fear them. But the Cat began to ſigh, and was excéed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly afraid, and ſaid, <hi>Reynard,</hi> what néeds many words? I have but ore wile, and that muſt help me, and forthwith hee clambered up to the top of a high Trée, where he lurk'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the leaves that neither Huntſman nor Hounds could hurt him, and left my Father to abide the whole hazard, for the whole Kennell purſued him, horns and hallows ecchoing after him: kill the Fox, kill the Fox.</p>
               <p>This when <hi>Tybert</hi> ſaw, he mocked my Father: and ſaid: New Couſin <hi>Reynard,</hi> it is time to let looſe all your wiles for if your wit foil you I fear your whole body will periſh. This my Father hearing from him he moſt truſted, and being then in the height of purſuit wearied, and almoſt ſpent, he let his male <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ip from his ſhoulders, to make himſelf ſo much lighter, yet all avai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed not, for the Hounds were ſo ſwift they had caught him, had he not by chance eſpied a hole, into which he entred, and eſcap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Hounds and Huntſmen. Thus you may ſée the falſe faith of the Cat, whoſe like there be many living at this time, and though this might well excuſe me from loving the Cat, yet my ſouls health and charity binds me to the contrary, and I wiſh him no hurt, though his misfortunes ſhall never be grievous to me: not ſo much for hatred, as the remembrance of his injuries, which often contends againſt my reaſon.</p>
               <p>Alſo in that Myrror ſtands another Hiſtory of the Wolf, how on a time he ſound upon a Heath a dead Horſe, whoſe fleſh being eaten away, he was ſain'to gnaw and devour the bones, which he did with ſuch gréedineſs, that ſwallowing them too haſtily down, one fell ſo croſſe his throat, that he was almoſt choak'd, and hardly eſcap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with life: whereupon
<pb facs="tcp:35919:61"/>he ſought every place for the cunningeſt Surgions promiſing them great gifts to eaſe his torments: but having loſt much labour, in the end he met with the Crane, and beſought him with his long neck and bill to help him, and he would high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reward him. The Crane gréedy of gain, put in his head into the Wolfs throat, and brought out the Bone. The Wolf ſtarted at the pull, and cried out aloud, thou hurt'ſt me, but I do forgive thee, yet do it not again I charge thee, for at anothers hands, I would not bear it: then the Crane ſaid: Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> go and be frolick, for you are whole, I look for no more but the reward you promiſed mée: How (ſaid the Wolf) what impudence is this? I ſuffer and have cauſe to complain, yet he will be rewarded, hée will not ſo much as thank me for his life, but forgets that his head was in my mouth, and how I ſuffered dim to draw it out again without hurting, albeit hée put me to excéeding much pain: I ſuppoſe it is I which deſerve the reward, and not the Crane.</p>
               <p>Thus you may ſée the faſhion of ungratefull men in théſe days, however they reward good with evill: for where as pride is exalted. there honour is ever laid in the duſt. There be a world which ought to reward, and do good to thoſe that have advanc'd them, which now complain, and make thoſe advancements injuries, but the gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on will follow: for it is the wiſeſt counſail, that whoſoever will go about to chaſtiſe another, ſhould ever be ſure of his own cleareneſs. All this, and a world more then I can well remember, was curiouſly wrought on this Glaſs: for the work-maſter thereof was the cunningeſt and profoundeſt Clark in all Sciences that ever breathed. And becauſe the Iewels were too good and precious for me to kéep, therfore I ſent them to the King &amp; Quéens Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties as a preſent, to witneſs my faith and ſervice: O hée that had ſéen what ſorrow my Children made when I ſent the Glaſs away! would have wondred; for by reaſon of the great vertue therein, they oft gazed in the ſame; both to behold themſelvs, and to ſée how their cloathing and apparell became them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:61"/>
               <p>Little did I then imagine that good <hi>Kyward</hi> was ſo néere his death, for then but himſelf, and <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ram, I knew no meſſenger worthy to carry ſo rich a preſent. But I will ſearch the whole world, but I will find the murtherer, for murther cannot be his. It may bée hée is in this preſence which knows what is become of <hi>Kvward,</hi> albeit he do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it; for many devi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s walk like Saints, Yet the greateſt wonder of all is (which troubled me moſt,) that my Lord the King thould ſay, that my Father, nor myſelf, ever did good. But the troubles of affaires may well bréed forgetfullneſs in Kings, otherwiſe your Majeſty might call to mind how when the King your Father lived, and you were a Prince not above two yeares old: My Father came from the School at <hi>Moun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pelio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> where he had ſtudied five years the Art of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and was expert in all the principles thereof; and ſo Famous in thoſe days, that he wore cloathes of Silk, and a Golden Girdle. Now when he was come to the Court hée found the King in great extremity of ſickneſs, (which was no little grief unto him, for he loved the King moſt dearly) and the King rejoiced at his ſight, and would not ſuffer him to be out of his preſence. All others might walk whither they would, onely hée muſt ever be néer him Then ſaid your Father, <hi>Reynard</hi> I am exceeding ſick, and I féel my ſickneſs increaſing. My Father anſwered; my Lord, here is a Vrinall, make water therein, and as ſoon as I behold your ſtate, I will give mine opinion. The King did as he was adviſed (for he tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted not any equall with him.) Then ſaid my Father, My beſt Lord, if you will be eaſed of your grief, you muſt needs eat the Liquor of a Wolf of ſeven yeares old, or elſe your diſeaſe is incurable.</p>
               <p>The Wolf at that time ſtood by your Father, but ſaid nothing: whereupon the King ſaid, Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> you heare how there is nothing which can cure mée but your Liquor. The Wolf replied: not ſo my Lord, ſor I am not yet full five yeares old. It is no matter (anſwered my Father) let him be opened, and when I ſée the Liquor, I will tell you if it bée medicinable: Then was the Wolf carried to the Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:62"/>and his Liquor taken out, which the King did eat, &amp; was preſently cured of his ſickneſs. Then the King thanked my Father and commanded all his Subjects on pain of death, from thenceforth to call him Maſter <hi>Reynard.</hi> ſo he abode ſtill about the King, walking by his ſide, and was truſted in all things and the King gave him (for an honour) a Garland of Roſes, which he muſt ever wear upon his head. But theſe remembrances are all loſt and gone, and his enemies are now onely advanced, vertue is put back, and Innocence li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es in ſorrow: for when baſeneſs and covetouſneſs are made Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, they neither know themſelvs, nor look at the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from whence they are riſen. They have no hearts for pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor ears for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> par mans cauſe. Gold is the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they run to, and gifts the god which they worſhip. What great mans Gate doth not look upon Covetouſneſs? where is not flattery entertained, and what Prince takes hate at his own praiſes? But ſhould greatneſs néed their honeſt ſervice, well might they ſtarve ere they could gain that imployment: For like Wolvs, they had rather ſée their Maſters dye, then lend them the leaſt part of their Liquor.</p>
               <p>This my Lord was an accident which fell in your youth, and you may well forget it: Yet (without boaſting) I my ſelf may ſay, I have done to you both honour and ſervice, and you haply alſo forget this which I ſhall repeat, which I vow I do not to upbraid your Majeſty, for you are ever worthy of more then I can tender, and my uttermoſt is but the rent of a loyall Subject, which I am ever bound by the lawes of God and nature to perform.</p>
               <p>So it was, that on a time <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf, and I had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a Swine under us, and by reaſon of his extreame lowd crying, we were compelled to bite him to death. At which time your ſelf came out of a Grove unto us, and ſaluted us friendly, ſaying: That you and the Qéen your wife which came after you, were both excéeding hungry, and intreated us to give you part of our getting: <hi>Iſegrim</hi> then whiſpered in ſuch manner, that none could underſtand him, but I ſpake out aloud: With all my heart my Lord, and were it better then
<pb facs="tcp:35919:62"/>it is, it were too mean for your ſervice. But <hi>Iſegrim</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his wont departed grumbling, and took half of the Swine, giving you and the Qeen but one poor quarter, the other he himſelf unmannerly devoured, and left me for my ſhare but p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>alf of the Lungs. When your Majeſty had eaten your part, you were ſtill hungry, but the Wolf would deliver none: ſo that you reach'd him a blow with your foot, which tore all the skin from about his eares, ſo that he ran aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y crying and howling with extremity. But you Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie commanded him to return again ſpéedily, and bring you more meat, but he went away grumbling. Then I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought your Majeſtly, that I might go with him: and I well remember your anſwer. So away we went together, his eares dropping blood all the way as he went: In the end we took a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>if, and when your Majeſty ſaw us bring it, you laughed, and ſaid to me, I was a ſwift Huntſman, and could finde my game quickly and therefore I was fit to ſerve in time of neceſſitie: Then you bade me to divide it, and I did it, and gave one half thereof to your Majeſty, the other half to the Quéen: As for the Muggets, Liver, Lungs and all the inwards, I ſent them to the young Princes your Children: As for the head I gave it to <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf, and took un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſelf but the féet onely. Then ſaid your Majeſty, ha <hi>Reyna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,</hi> who taught you to make theſe courteous diviſions? My Lord (anſwered I) that did this Prieſt which ſits here with his bloodly pate: for he loſt his skin for his too much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality, and for his covetouſneſs hath reap'd nothing but ſhame and diſhonour. But it matters not, for there be many Wolvs in theſe days, that would even eat up their beſt friends and kindred: Nay if they had power, even your Majeſty alſo, for they make no reſpect either of friend or enemy. But woe to that Common-wealth where ſuch have the upper hand and goverment.</p>
               <p>My gracious Lord, this and many ſuch like actions as this have I done for your Majeſty, which were it not for tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake, I could well repeat. But they are all now caſt out of your remembrance, but time and my loyalty I hope will
<pb facs="tcp:35919:63"/>one day again recall them. I have ſéen the day when no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was finiſhed in the Court without my advice and cenſure, though now that Iudgment is not ſo reputed: yet it may be, the ſame reputation may ſpring up again, and be believed as firmely as before, as long as it ſwerves not from Iuſtice, which is the onely thing I aim at. For if any one can charge me otherwiſe, and prove it by witneſs, here I ſtand to indure the uttermoſt the Law can inflict upon me: But if malice onely ſlander me without witneſs, I crave the combate accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law and inſtance of the Court. Then ſaid the King, <hi>Reynard,</hi> you ſay well; nor know I any thing more of <hi>Kywards</hi> death, then the bringing of his head unto me by <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> the Ram; therefore of it I here acquit you. My dear Lord (ſaid the Fox) I humbly thank you: yet is his death ſo griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto me, I cannot let it paſs ſo eaſie: I remember my heart was heavy at his departure, and I was ready to ſink to the ground, which was a certain preſage of the loſſe which happened.</p>
               <p>Theſe words, and the ſad looks of the Fox, ſo amazed all the beholders, that they could not chuſe but believe all that he uttered, ſo that every one bemoan'd his loſs, and pittied his ſorrow. But the King and Qéen were moſt touched with the ſame, and then intreated him that he would make diligent ſearch for the finding of them out, for his praiſes had ſtricken them far in love with the Iewels? And becauſe he told them, he had ſent thoſe Iewels unto them (though they never ſaw them) yet they gave him as great thanks, as if they had béen in their ſafe poſſeſſion, and deſired him he would be a meanes they might be reſtored to them again.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the relation which the Fox made of the Jewels, and their ſeveral virtues and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, is ſhewed the policy of the wicked, which are ever prepared of thoſe baits which they know wil ſoo n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> catch the minds of them they are to intangle. as wealth health, honour &amp; vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, all which be lodged in thoſe Jewels. As for the ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries conteined in them, the Fox doth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralize them himſelf, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them ſeverally, the imputations he would have the Lion know to be in his enemies, &amp; ſuch examples are evermore bitter, and work more in the mindes or the hearts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpeech or invection whatſoever. By the repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his and his Fathers ſervices, is ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, he ſubtil inſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which to extenuate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent crimes, call to minde their good deeds Paſt not ſo much for the memory of the good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, as to beg a new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward though it have bin ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo often paid for; for noble ſpirits have ever a tender ſeeing, and are ſoon toucht with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of any good turns re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for it is an obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom cancell.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:63"/>
               <head>CHAP. 22. How <hi>Reynard</hi> made his peace wich the King, and how <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf complained of him again.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>Then the King anſwered him, that ſo ſoon as it ſhould be known where they were, no help or aſſiſtance ſhould be wanting. The Fox gave the King humble thanks, for now he had gotten all his purpoſes to the wiſhed end he expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by his falſe tale and flatterie, had ſo faſtned the King unto him, that now he might go freely whither he pleaſed, and none ſhould dare to complain upon him: onely <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf ſtood all this while infinitely diſpleaſed, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to contein his anger any longer; he ſaid, O my Lord the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is it poſſible your Majeſtie ſhould be ſo much childiſh or weak of belief, as to fix your truſt upon the falſhood of this ever-deceiving merchant, which hath nothing but ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and Chymera's wherewith to inchant you? O be not ſo eaſily ſeduced, he is a wretchall covered and beſmeared with murther and treaſon, and even to your own face hath made a ſcoffe of your Majeſtie. For my own part I am glad hee is here in your preſence, and I intend to ring him ſuch a peal of contray nature, that all the lies he can invent, ſhall not bear him away with ſafety.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>But <hi>Reynard</hi> anſwered, and ſaid, If this were true, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it would touch me near in honour and reputation: but God forbid that ſuch a ſlaunder ſhould bee proved againſt
<pb facs="tcp:35919:65"/>me. I confeſſe I taught her to catch fiſh, and taught her how to enter the water, and never touch the mire: but her gréedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſo tranſported her when ſhe heard me name the fiſh, that ſhee ran without reſpect of any path or direction; and ſo comming into the Ice, the was there preſently frozen, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her too long tarrying; for ſhe had more fiſh then would have ſatisfied twentie reaſonable appetites: but it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſeen, that who all would have, all forego: for covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſeldom bringeth any thing well home: yet when I ſaw her ſo faſtned in the Ice, I uſed all my beſt indeavours to looſen her, and ſo indéed was heaving and ſhoving about her, but to little purpoſé; for by reaſon of her weight I was not able to move her.</p>
               <p>Now whilſt this was in doing came <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> and ſéeing me ſo buſie about her, Churle-like hée moſt vilely ſlandered me, like a profuſe Wittal, which takes delight to bée accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Cuckold: but believe it, my gracious Lord, all was falſe, and his wife virtuous, for any thing within my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: whence I am perſwaded, that ſurely his eye dazled; for indéed he uttered many a grievous curſe, and threatned much revengement againſt me; ſo that more to eſchew his blaſphemy then fury. I went my way, and he came; and with as great ado, and as much heave and ſhove, he helpt her out: which done, (they then almoſt ſtarved with cold) ran and ſkipt up and down the fields to get them heat: and that this is all truth which I have ſpoken, I will willingly be depoſed, for I would not be the father of any falſhood before your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, to be maſter of many millions: however my fortunes go, I reſpect not, truth is my badge, and hath ever been the Enſigne of all my Anceſtors: and if there be any ſcruple or doubt made of mine aſſertion, I aſke but eight daies li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, that I may confer with my learned Counſel, and I will ſo approve all my words by the oath and teſtimony of good and ſufficient witneſſe, that your Majeſtie, and your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Counſel ſhall accord to the juſtneſſe of my prete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation. As for the Wolf, what have I to do with him? It is well known already that he is a debauſht and almoſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="tcp:35919:66"/>villain; falſe both to heaven and to your Majeſtie, and now his own words witneſſe him a baſe ſlanderer of women: therefore I refer my ſelf to the trial of his wife: if ſhe accuſe me, let the world hold me guilty; provided ſhe may be made frée from her husband, whoſe tyranny will compell her to ſay any thing, though never ſo unjuſtly.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Then ſaid dame <hi>Arſewinde</hi> to the King: I beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, mark how this diſſembler can blow with all windes, and paint his miſchiefs with falſe colours: a world of times hath he brough me into theſe hazards. Once he betrai'd me to my Aunt the ſhee-Ape, where ere I eſcaped, I was fain to leave one of mine ears behind me: if the Fox dare tell the truth of the ſtory (for I know his memorie to be much better: beſides he is apt to catch advantage from the weakneſſe of language) I deſire no better evidence againſt him. Then ſaid the Fox, willingly I will do it, and without flattery or falſhood, and therefore I beſéech your Majeſtie lend me your Royal patience.</p>
               <p>Vpon a certain time the Wolf here came to me into the Wood, and complained unto me that he was exceeding hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:67"/>(yet never ſaw him fuller in my life) but he would ever diſſemble: at which preſently I took pity of him, and ſaid, I was alſo as hungry as he: ſo away he went and travelled half a day together without finding any thing; then began he to whine and crie, and ſaid, he was able to go no further. Then hard by the foot of a Hathorn trée, we eſpied a hole all covered over with Brambles, and heard a great ruſhing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but could not imagin the cauſe why: then I deſired the Wolf to go in and look if any thing were there to profit us, (for ſome thing I knew there was) then ſaid he; Couſin, I would not créep into the hole for a hundred pounds, till I know cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly what was therein, for there may be danger: but if you pleaſe to attempt it, who I know hath both Art and wit to ſave your ſelf, I will ſtay here under this Trée till you return: but I beſéech you make haſte, and let me know what is there in as ſoon as you perceive it.</p>
               <p>Behold, my dread Lord the King thus he hath made me poor ſilly beaſt to go before into the hazard, and he who is great, ſtrong, and mighty, did abide without in peace, wherein I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt no little friendſhip, for I would not endure the like dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for a Kingdom: but to procéed, I entered into the hole, and found the way dark, long, and tedious: in the end I eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great light, which came in on the further ſide of the hole, by which I ſaw there lying a great ſhée-Ape, with eies glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering and ſparkling with fire, her mouth ſet round with long ſharp téeth, and on her hands and nails ſharp as an Elſin, or Bodkin. I imagined her at firſt a Marmazin, or Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boon, or elſe a Mercat, for a more dreadful beaſt I never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held in all my life time; and by her ſide lay divers of her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which like her ſelfe were cruel and ſterne of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: when they ſaw me come towards them, they gaped wide with their mouths upon me, ſo that I grew amazed, and wiſh'd my ſelf far from the harbor. But reſolving with my ſelf, that now I was in, I muſt quit my ſelf as well as I could; I looked more conſtantly upon her, and me thought ſhe appeared bigger then <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf, and the leaſt of her brats much larger then my ſelf (for a fouler
<pb facs="tcp:35919:67"/>company I never ſaw) they were all laid in foul litter, rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and durtie, with their own piſſe, they were all daubed and clogged with their own dung, which ſtunk ſo filthie, that I was almoſt poiſoned with the ſmell. For my own part I durſt not but ſpeak them fair, and therefore I ſaid, Aunt, God give you many good daies, and bleſſe you and my Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins your prettie children: queſtionleſſe they are the ſaireſt of their ages that ever I beheld, and ſo ſurpaſſe in beautie and perfection, that they may well be accounted of moſt princely iſſue. I ruly Aunt, we are infinitely beholden to you that doth adde this increaſe and glorie to your familie. For mine own part (dear Aunt) when I heard you were laid down and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, I could not ſtay, but needs muſt come and viſit you: Then replied ſhe, Couſin <hi>Reynard,</hi> you are exceeding wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: you have found me like a ſlut, but I thank you for your kinde viſitation: you are a worthie Gentleman, and (thorow the Kings Dominions) for your wit and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, held of ſingular reputation; you do much honour to our kindred, and are famous for the means you work to their preterment: I muſt intreat you to take the charge of my children, and inſtruct them in the rules of knowledge and ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay know hereafter how to live in the world. I have thought of you ever ſince they were born, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon this, Couſin becauſe I knew your perfection, and that you accompanied your ſelf with none but the good and the virtuous.</p>
               <p>O how glad was I when I heard thoſe words to proceed from her, which kindneſſe was onely becauſe at firſt I called her Aunt, who indeed was no foul kin unto me: for my true Aunt indeed is onely dame <hi>Ruk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>naw,</hi> which ſtandeth yonder: who indeed is mother of excellent children. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I anſwered this foul monſter; Aunt, my life and goods are both at your ſervice, and what I can do for you night or day, ſhall ever be at your commandement and your childrens. Yet. I moſt heartily wiſht my ſelf farre from them at that inſtant, for I was almoſt poiſoned with their ſtink. And I pitied <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> who was ſore griped with
<pb facs="tcp:35919:68"/>hunger all this while? and offering to take my leave, and fain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing that my wife will think it long till my returne, She ſaid, Dear Couſin, you ſhall not depart till you have ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſomething, I ſhall take it unkindly if you offer it, then roſe wee up, and carried mee into an inner Room, where was great ſtore of all kinde of Veniſon: both the Red Deer, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llow Deer, and Roe: and great ſtore of Partridge, Pheaſant, and other Fowls, that I amazed much from whence ſuch ſtore of meat ſhould come. Now when I had eaten ſufficiently, ſhe gave me a ſide and half a haunch of a Hinde, to carrie home to my Wife, which I was aſhamed to take, but that ſhe compelled me: and ſo taking my leave, and being intreated often to viſit her, I did depart thence, much joied that I had ſped ſo well.</p>
               <p>Now being come out of the Cauſey, I ſpied whereas <hi>Iſegrim</hi> lay groaning pitifully, and I asked him how he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? He ſaid, wondrous ill, and ſo extreamly ill, that (dear Nephew) without ſome meat I die preſently: then did I take compaſſion on him, and gave him my wifes Token, which preſerved his life, and for which then he gave me a world of thanks, though now he hate me extreamly. But as ſoon as he had devoured up my Veniſon, he ſaid, <hi>Reynard,</hi> my dear Couſin, what found you in the hole? believe it I am now more hungrie then I was before, and this ſmall morſel hath but ſharpned my téeth to eat more. Then ſaid I to him, Vncle, get yon into that hole, and you ſhall find ſtore of victuals, for there lieth my Aunt with her children: if you can flatter and ſpeak her fair, you néed fear no hard meaſure, all things will be as you would wiſh it.</p>
               <p>I think (my gracious Lord) this was warning ſufficient, and that which might have armed any wiſe ſpirit, but rude and barbarous beaſts will never underſtand wiſedom. And therefore they loath the policies they know not. But yet he promiſed to follow my counſel: ſo forth he went into that foul ſtinking hole, and found the Ape in that filthie ſort as before I deſcribed, which when he ſaw, (being affrighted) he cried out, Wo and alas, I think I am come into hell: did
<pb facs="tcp:35919:68"/>ever creature ſée ſuch fearful goblins? drown them, for ſhame drown them, they are ſo ugly, they are able to ſcare the Divel, why they make my hair ſtand an end with their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid deformitie. Then (ſaid ſhe) Sir <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egrim,</hi> their creation is not my fault, ſet it ſuffice, they are my children, and I am their Mother. Nor ought their beautie or hard favour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe you: here was a kinſman of theirs to day, and is but newly departed, who is well known to exceed you both in birth, virtue and wiſdome, and he accounted them fair and lovely, for your opinion I care not: therefore you may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part at your pleaſure. Then he repli'd (Dame) I would have you know, that I would eat of your meat, it is much better beſtowed one mee, then on thoſe uglie Vrchins. But ſhe told him, ſhe had no meat: Yes (ſaid he) here is meat enough, and with that, offering to reach at the meat, my Aunt ſtart up with her children, and ran at him with their ſharpe nailes and ſo clawed him, that the blood ran about his eares, and I heard him erie and howle ſo extreamly, that it appeared he had no defence, but to run out of the hole, as faſt as he could. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed he came out both extreamly beaten, and extreamly bitten, and all his skin ſlaſht like a Spaniſh Ierkin: and one year left behind as a paune of his manners.</p>
               <p>This when I ſaw, I asked him if he had flattred ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently? and he ſaid he had ſpoken as he found, for the Damme was a foule Bitch, and the Litter moſt ugly monſters. Then I told him, how he ſhould have commended their beauties, and take them for his beſt of alliance. And he replied, he had rather have ſéen them all hang'd. Then (quoth I) you muſt alwaies receive ſuch reward as now you do, but wiſdome would do otherwiſe, a lie ſomtimes as much a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eth, as a true tale: and faire words never come out of ſeaſon, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then we, hold it for a rule worthy Imitation.</p>
               <p>Thus my Lord, I have told you truly how he came by his red night-cap, which I know he ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mot, nor dare to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for all is true without any addition.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Wolf, is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the envie that one ill man bears ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and how loath they are that any of their contrary faction ſhould ſcape puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that to gain reve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they care not what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie they do to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as doth appear by the Wolfs ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own wife. By the riſing of the Town up againſt the Wolf and his wife, is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that one miſchief ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom cometh to all folks, but another ſtill follows it at the heels. By the Foxes excuſe, is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, how policy hath ever an evaſion, or a cloak for any evil it doth, &amp; can colour e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with a preſence of goodneſſe. The Foxes contempt of the Wolf, ſhews, that the ſtrength or policie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe part, and calling his good name in queſtion, by which means he may loſe his life and credit. By the ſhee-Wolfs falling into the well. ſhewes the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, which never brings any thing home but loſſe and danger; and that policie cares not who pines, ſo he feel no pain, as appears by the Foxes tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting her into the Bucket. By their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the ſhe Apes Cave is ſhewed, the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and how far good words will prevail before rude and churliſh behaviour.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:69"/>
               <head>CHAP. 23. How <hi>Iſegrim</hi> profered his Glove to <hi>Reynard</hi> to fight with him, which <hi>Reynard</hi> accepted; and how <hi>Rukenaw</hi> adviſed the Fox how to carrie himſelf in the fight.</head>
               <p>THe Wolf anſwered the Fox: I may well forbear (falſe Villain, as thou art) thy mocks and ſcorns, but thine injuries I will not. You ſay, I was almoſt dead for hunger, when you helpt me in my need: but thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieſt falſely therein, for it was nothing but a Hare-bone thou gaveſt me, when thou hadſt gnawed all the meat thereof: and therefore know in this thou injureſt my reputation; again, thou accuſeſt me of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt the King and to conſpire his Majeſties death, for certain treaſure thou ſaieſt is in <hi>Huſterloe:</hi> alſo thou haſt abuſed and ſlandered my wife, which will ever be an infamie to her name, if it be not revenged: theſe things conſidered, I have for born you long therefore now look not to eſcape; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſéeing there is no other teſtimony but out own conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; here before you my Lord the King, and the reſt of my Noble Lords, friends and alliances, here I will affirm, and approve to the loſt drop of my blood, that thou <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox, art a faiſe Traitor and a murtherer; and this I will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and make good upon thy bodie within the Liſts of the field bodie againſt bodie by which means our ſtrife ſhall have an end; and in witneſſe whereof I caſt thée here my Glove, which I dare thée to take up, that I may have right for mine injuries, or elſe die like a Recreant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reynard</hi> was ſomthing perplexed when he ſaw this, for he knew himſelf much too weak for the Wolf, and feared to come by the worſt: but ſtraight remembring the advantage he had, by reaſon the Wolfs fore-claws were pulled away, and that they were not yet fully cured, he ſaid, Whatſoever he be that ſaith I am a Traitor, or a murtherer, I ſay he lieth in his throat, eſpecially <hi>Iſegrim</hi> above all others: poor fool, thou bringeſt me to the place I deſire, and to the purpoſe I wiſh for, in ſigne whereof I take up the gage, and throw down mine, to approve all thy words, lies and falſhoods.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:69"/>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p>When theſe ceremonies were done, the Marſhalls of the Field bad them do their devoir. And then every creature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided the Liſts, ſave Dame <hi>Rukenaw,</hi> who ſtood by the Fox, and had him remember the words and inſtructions ſhe had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, and call to minde, how when he was ſcarce ſeven years old, he had then wiſdom enough to piſſe the darkeſt night, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Lanthorn or Candle-light, or the help of the Moon, when any occaſion required him: and that his experience was much greater, and his reputation of wiſdome more frequent with his companions: and therefore to work ſo as he might win the day, which would be an eternal monument to him and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily for ever. To this the Fox anſwered (My beſt Aunt) aſſure your ſelf I will do my beſt, and not forget a tittle of your counſel, I doubt not but my friends ſhall reap honour and my foes ſhame by my actions: to this the Ape ſaid, Amen; and ſo departed.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lfs challenging the Combat of the Fox, is ſhewed the madneſſe of rage &amp; fury, &amp; how negligent it is in reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting his own hazard, ſo it may do miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe to the adverſary. The Foxes accepting of it thewes how when policy hath no other ſhiſting hole, that then it growes deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and will out-face any thing to the uttermoſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. By the ſhe Apes counſell is ſhewed, the care of a true friend, which is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en ever moſt buſie, when he ſees his companion in danger, and leaves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o way unſought that way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ree him from trouble.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. 24. Of the Combate betwixt the Fox and the Wolf; the event, paſſages, and victori.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>WHen none but the Combatants were in the Liſts, the Wolf went toward the Fox with infinite rage and furie, and thinking to take the Fox in his fore-feet, the Fox leapt nimbly from him, and the Wolf purſued him; ſo that there began a tedious chaſe between them, on which their friends gaxed. The Wolfe taking larger ſtrides then the Fox, often overtook him; and lifting up his feet to ſtrike him, the Fox avoided the blow, and ſmote him on the face with his tail, which was all to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iſt; ſo that the Wolf was ſtricken almoſt blinde, the piſſe ſmarted ſo extreamly. And he was forced to reſt while he glaired his eies, which advantage when <hi>Reynard</hi> ſaw, he ſcratched up the duſt with his feet, and threw it in the eies of the Wolf. This grieved him worſe then the former, ſo that he durſt follow him no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for the duſt and ſand ſticking in his eies ſmarted ſo ſore,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:73"/>that of force he muſt rub and waſh it away, which <hi>Reynard</hi> ſéeing, with all the furie he had he ran upon him, and with his téeth gave him thrée fore wounds on his head, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing ſaid; have I hit you Mr. Wolf? I will yet hit you bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: you have kill'd many a Lamb, and many an innocent beaſt, and would impoſe the fault upon me, but you ſhall finde the price of your knavery: I am markt to puniſh thy ſins, and I will give thee thy abſolution bravely. It is good thou uſe patience, for Hell is Purgatory, and thy life is at my mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: Yet notwithſtanding, if thou will kneel down, and aske me forgiveneſſe, and confeſſe thy ſelf vanquiſhed (though thou béeſt the worſt thing living) yet I will ſpare thy life, for my pity makes me loath to kill thee. Theſe words made <hi>Iſogrim</hi> both mad and deſperate, ſo that he knew not how to expreſſe his fury; his wounds bled, his eies ſmarted, and his whole body was oppreſſed. So that in the height of his fury he lift up his foot, and ſtruck the Fox ſo great a blow, that he fell'd him to the ground. But <hi>Reynard</hi> being nimble, quickly roſe up again, and encountered the Wolf, that between them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun a dreadful and doubtful combate. The Wolf was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding furious, and ten time he leaped to catch <hi>Reynard</hi> faſt, but his skin was ſo ſlippery and oylie, he could not hold him. Nay, ſo wondrous nimble was he in the fight, that when the Wolf thought to have him ſureſt, he would ſhift himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his legs, and under his bellie, and every time gave the Wolf a bite with his téeth, or a ſwap on the face with his tail, that the poor Wolf found nothing but deſpair in the conflict, albeit his ſtrength was much the greater.</p>
               <p>Thus, many wounds and bitings paſſing on either ſide; the one expreſſing cuning, and the other ſtrength; the one fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the other temperance. In the end the Wolf being inra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that the battel had continued ſo long (for had his feet been ſound, it had been much ſhorter) he ſaid to himſelf, I will make an end of this combate; for, I know my very weight is able to cruſh him to pieces, and I loſe much of my reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſuffer him thus long to contend againſt me. And this ſaid, he ſtruck the Fox again ſo ſore a blow on the head
<pb facs="tcp:35919:73"/>with his foot, that he fell down to the ground, and ere he could recover himſelf, and ariſe, he caught him in his feet, and threw him under him; lying upon him in ſuch wiſe, as if he would have preſt them to death.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Now began the Fox to bée grievouſly afraid, and all his friends alſo, and all <hi>Iſegrims</hi> friends began to ſhout for joy:
<pb facs="tcp:35919:74"/>but the Fox defended himſelf (as well as he could) with his claws, lying along, and the Wolf could not hurt him with his claws, his feet were ſo ſore; onely with his teeth he ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to bite him: which when the Fox ſaw, he ſmote the Wolf on the head with his fore claws, ſo that he tore the skin between his brows, and his ears and one of his eies hung out of his head, which put the Wolf to infinite torment, and he howled out extremely: then <hi>Iſegrim</hi> wiping his face, the Fox took advantage thereof, and with his ſtrugling got upon his feet.</p>
               <p>At which the Wolf was angrie, and ſtriking after him, caught the Fox in his arms, and held him faſt: never was <hi>Reynard</hi> in ſo great a ſtrait as then, for at that time great was their contention: but anger now made the Wolf forget his ſmart: and griping the Fox altogether under him, as <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> was deſending himſelf, his hand light into <hi>Iſegrims</hi> mouth, ſo that he was in danger to loſe it. Then ſaid the Wolf to the Fox, now either yield thy ſelf as vanquiſhed, or elſe certainly I will kill thee; neither thy duſt, thy piſſe, thy mocks, nor any ſubtil invention ſhall now ſave thee, thou art now left utterly deſperate, and my wounds muſt have their ſatisfaction. When the Fox heard this, he thought it was a hard election, for both brought his ruine; and ſuddenly concluding, he ſaid; Dear Vncle, ſince fortune commands me, I yield to be your ſervant; and at your commandement will travel for you to the Holy Land, or any other Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or do any ſervice which ſhall be beneficial to your ſoul, or the ſoul of your fore-fathers: I will do for the King, or for our holy father the Pope: I will hold of you my Lands and revenues; and as I ſo ſhall all the reſt of my kindred; ſo that you ſhall be a Lord of many Lords, and none ſhall dare to move againſt you: Beſides, whatſoever I get of Pullins, Geeſe, Partringes or P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oter, fleſh or fiſh, you, your wife and children ſhall h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve the firſt choice ere any come in my belly. I will ever ſtand by your ſide, and whereſoever you go, no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhall come ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r you: you are ſtrong, and I am ſubtil, we two joined together, what force can prevail againſt us:
<pb facs="tcp:35919:74"/>Again, wee are ſo near in blood, that nature forbids there ſhould be any enmitie between us: I would not have fought againſt you, had I been ſure of victory, but that you firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed me, and then you know of neceſſity I muſt do my ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt: I have alſo in this battel been courteous to you, and not ſhews my worſt violence, as I would on a ſtranger, for I know it is the dutie of a Nephew to ſpare his Vncle: and this you might well perceive by my running from you, I tell you it was an acion much contrary to my nature; for I might often have hurt you when I refuſed, nor are you worſe for me by any thing, more then the blemiſh of your eie, for which I am ſorrie, and with it had not hapned: yet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by know that you ſhal reap rather benefit then loſe thereby, for when other Beaſts in their ſleep ſhut two windows, you ſhall ſhut but o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. As for my wife, children, and lineage, they ſhall fall down at your feet before you in any preſence: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I humbly deſire you that you will ſuffer poor <hi>Reynard</hi> to live. I know you will kill me, but what will that avail you, when you ſhall never live in ſafety for fear of reverg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my kindred? Therefore temperance many man's wrath is excellent, whereas reſhneſſe is ever the mother of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance but Vncle, I know you to be valiant, wiſe, and diſcreet, and you rather ſeek honor, peace, and good ſame, then blood and revenge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf ſaid; Infinite diſſembler, how fain wouldſt thou be free'd of my ſervitude? Too well I underſtand thee, and know that if thou were ſafe on thy féet, thou wouldſt forſwear this ſubmiſſion: but know, all the wealth in the world ſhall not buy out thy ranſome; for thee and thy friends I eſteem them not, nor believe any thing thou haſt uttered: too well I know thee and am no bird for thy Lime-buſh chaffe cannot deceive me: O how wouldſt thou triumph, if I ſhould believe thee; and ſay I wanted wit to underſtand thee but thou ſhalt know, I can look both on this ſide, and beyond thee; thy many deceits uſed upon me, have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow armed me againſt thée. Thou ſaiſt thou haſt ſpared me in the battel: but look upon me, and my wounds will ſpew how falſely thou lieſt,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:75"/>thou never gaveſt me a time to breath in, nor will I now give thée a minute to repent in; and the rather when I think of the diſhonour thou didſt to my bed, and how inhumanely thou didſt raviſh my dear wife, Dame <hi>Arſewinde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now whilſt <hi>Iſegrim</hi> was thus talking, the Fox be thought himſelf how he might beſt get free, and thruſting his other hand down between his leggs, he caught the Wolf faſt by the ſtones, and he wrung him ſo extreamly and hard thereby, that he made him ſhrink and howl out with the anguiſh: then the Fox drew his other hand out of his mouth, for the Wolf was in ſuch wondrous torment, that he had much ado to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein himſelf from ſwounding: for this torment exceeded above the pain of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie, and in the end he fell over and over in a ſwound: then preſently <hi>Reynard</hi> leapt upon, and drew him about thè Liſts, and dragg'd him by the legs, and ſtruck, wounded, and bit him in many places, ſo that all the whole field might take notice thereof.</p>
               <p>At this all Iſegrims friends were full of ſorrow, and with great weeping and lamenting went to the King, and praied him to be pleaſed to appeaſe the combat, and take it into his own hands: which ſuit the King granted, and then the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard and the Leſſon (being marſhals) entered the Liſts, and told the Fox and the Wolf that the King would ſpeak with them, and that the battel ſhould there end, for he would take it into his own hands, and determine thereof: as for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they had done ſufficiently, neither would the Kingloſe either of them: and to the Fox they ſaid, the whole field gave him the victory.</p>
               <p>The Fox ſaid, I humbly thank them, and what pleaſeth my Lord the King to command, I am ready to obey, for mine ambition is no further then to be victor: therefore I beſéech you let my friends come to attend me, that I may procéed by their advice. They anſwered, it was reaſon: ſo preſently came forth dame <hi>Slopecard</hi> and <hi>Grimbart</hi> her husband, dame <hi>Rukenaw</hi> with her two ſiſters, <hi>Bitelus</hi> and <hi>Fulrumpe</hi> her two ſons, and <hi>Malice</hi> her daughter, the field Mouſe, the Weaſel, and above an hundred which would not have come,
<pb facs="tcp:35919:75"/>if the Fox had loſt the conqueſt: for to him that hath honour, will over flock attendants; but to him that is in loſſe, will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but contempt follow. Alas, the Fox came to the Bever, the Otter &amp; both their wives <hi>Pauntcerrote,</hi> and <hi>Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gale,</hi> and the <hi>Olt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> the <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chews,</hi> the <hi>Firri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the <hi>Squirril,</hi> and a world more then I can name, and all becauſe hée was the victor: nay divers which before had complained of him, were now of neareſt kindred; and ready to do him all ſervice. This is the faſhion of the world, he that is rich and in favour, can never be poor or hungry for friendſhip, every one will ſeem to love him, every one will imitate his faſhions.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Then was a ſolemne feaſt held; Trumpets were ſounded, Cornets winded, ſhawms, and all inſtruments warbled, and every one cried, Praiſed be heaven for this glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. <hi>Reynard</hi> thanked them all kindely, and received them with great joy and gladneſſe: then asked their opinions whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould yield the victory to the King or no: and Dame
<pb facs="tcp:35919:76"/>
                  <hi>Slopard</hi> ſaid, yea by all meanes Couſin, for it ſtands with your honour, nor may you deny it. And (ſo the Marſhalls going before) they went all to the King, garding the Fox on every ſide, all the Trumpets, Pipes and Minſtrills ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before him.</p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:76"/>
               <p>When <hi>Reynard</hi> came before the King, he fell on his knées, and the King bade him ſtand up and ſaid to him <hi>Reynard,</hi> you may well rejoice, for you have wen much honour our this day; therefore here I diſcharge you and ſet you frée, to go whither your own will leads you, for all conteſtations I ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e upon my ſelf, and will have it diſcuſt by the wiſeſt of the Kingdom, as ſoon as <hi>Iſegrims</hi> wounds ſhal be cured, at what time I wil ſend for you, and ſo procéed to judgment.</p>
               <p>My worthie and dread Lord (ſaid the Fox) I am well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid with any thing that ſhall pleaſe you: yet when I came firſt to your Highneſſe Court, there were many malicious perſons which ſought my life (whom I never injured) but they thought to overcome me, by joining with mine enemies againſt me, and thinking the Wolf had greater favour then I with your Majeſty: this was the ground of their indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein they ſhewed their ſimplicitie, not to alter the end which followed.</p>
               <p>Theſe men (my Lord) are like a great kennel of Hounds which once I ſaw ſtanding at a Lords houſe on a dunghill, where they waited for ſuch as ſhould bring them meat, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non they ſaw a Hound come out of the Kitchen, which had thence brought a goodly rib of Beef: but the Cook purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, threw hot ſcalding water after him, and ſcalded all his hinder parts: but notwithſtanding away he went with his booty: but when his fellows perceived him, they called to him, and ſaid; O how much art thou bound to the good Cook which hath given thee that goodly bone ſo well furniſhed with fleſh; but the Dog replied, You ſpeak accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your knowledg, and praiſe me in ſuch ſort, as you ſee me before with the bone in my mouth; but if you pleaſe to look upon me behinde on my buttocks, you ſhall finde how dearly I paid for it; and they beholding how he was ſcalded, and all the hair and skin flayed from his hinder loins: they began to be agaſt and amazed at his torment; neither would they any more of his fellowſhip, but fled and ran away from him. In the ſame ſort (my Lord) theſe faiſe and unworthie Beaſts, when they are made Lords, poſſeſſe
<pb facs="tcp:35919:77"/>their deſires, and are mighty and renowned: then do they extort, pill and pell the poor and needy, and cat them up like ſo many hungry ſtarved Hounds; for they are the dogs with bones in their mouths, no man dare to meddle with them, but praiſe all their actions: no man dare offend them; nay, many aſſiſt and help them in their unlawful actions, onely that they may lick their fingers, and be partakers of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortions</p>
               <p>O (my dear Lord)! how can thoſe men go ſafely, which go thus blind-fould? Or how can they expect but a ſhameful fall, whoſe ſteps are ſo uncertain? neither can any man pity them when their works are diſcloſed; but continual curſes and upbraidings follow them to the grave with deſtruction: many of theſe have loſt their hair (which is their friends) as the Hound did, and have none left to cover their miſchiefs, but all forſake them as the Hounds did the dog which was ſcalded.</p>
               <p>My gracious Lord, I beſéech you remember this moral ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and it will nothing impair the greatneſſe of your vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, for doubtleſſe mary of theſe evil exrorting creatures are under your ſubjection, both in Towns, Cities, and great Lords houſes, who out-face the poor, and ſell away their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and privileges, and threaten things upon them which they never knew, thought, or imagined, and all to make up the Common-wealths of their own particular profits: but the ends of ſuch are vile, and heaven hath for them a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but of theſe errors I hope none ſhall juſtly accuſe me, nor any of my kindred, but we ſhall acquite us nobly from the ſame, I fear no creatures accuſations; For I will ever be the Fox, though all my foes ſwear to the contrary. My Lord, you I adore above all mortal creatures living; nor can any wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom divert me from you, but I will abide by you to the laſt gaſp: and though malice have told your Highneſſe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, yet I have ever diſproved them, and ſo will do to the laſt moment.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lfs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing the Fox, and the Foxes watching and purſuing of advantages, is ſhewed, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olly of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>age &amp; paſſion, and the diſcretion of temperance and wiſdome; the firſt never bringing any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, the other commonly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with honour and ſafetie. By the piſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>il is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, the ſharp afflictions with which wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ever pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh as raſhness, and by the loſſe of the Wolfs eie, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hewed, that madneſſe and rage is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lindneſſe. The Wolfs catching the <hi>Fox,</hi> and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, power, ſhews, that ſo ſure ſomtime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>avour, fools, but never gives them grace to enjoy the benefit The Foxes flatt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing of the Wolf, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ws, That whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wiſdom is oppreſſed, it hath yet ſtill one temperate means or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to gain his own liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and that fair words do ever either vanquiſh, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh Laſtly, by the weak Foxes conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtrong Wolf, is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that in all theſe accidents of change, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther force, rage, nor violence do prevail ſo much as wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and wary carriage.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:77"/>
               <head>CHAP. 25. How the King forgave the Fox all things, and made him the greateſt in his Land; and of his noble return home with all his kindred.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>All <hi>Reynards</hi> friends and kindred humbly thanked the King, but he told them it was much ſhort of that he intended to do for their ſakes; and adviſed them all to admoniſh him to be careful of his faith and loialty. This ſaid Dame <hi>Ruke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naw,</hi> Believe it my Lord, we will not fail in that point, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fear you the contrary? for ſhould he prove otherwiſe, we would renounce him. Then the Fox alſo thanked the King with fair and courteous words, ſaying; My gracious Lord! I am not worthie of theſe high honours you do me, yet will ever ſtudie with my ſervice how to deſerve them: nor ſhal my beſt counſel at any time be wanting. And this ſaid, he took his humble leave of the King, and ſo departed with the reſt of his friends and kindred.</p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:79"/>
               <p>Amongſt the reſt, <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox took his leave of the King and Quéen, they deſired him not to be long abſent from them. To whom he anſwered, that he would be ever ready at their ſervice, as was his bounden duty; and not himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but all his friends and kindred alſo. And ſo begging li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of his Majeſtie in all ſolemne manner, and with fair ſpéech, he departed the Court.</p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:79"/>
               <p>Was never creature that ever flatterd braver, or to better purpoſe, for he that could do the like might be a Maſter of the eight liberall Sciences. And no Lord whether Spirituall or Temporall, but would have an eare open for all his language. Nor dyed he without iſſue, for he hath Children almoſt in all places.</p>
               <p>And indéed he that hath no alliance to him in the Art of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation, ſhall hardly proſper, as the world goeth: Though he want his heir, yet if he have his heart, it is enough to make him accepted.</p>
               <p>Plain dealing is now an exile, and Coveteouſneſs and fraud have taken poſſeſſion of his Tenements: not the Popes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, the Court of Emperours, Kings and Princes cannot be excepted of this error.</p>
               <p>Money is now grown the onely Favorite of the times; the very Church-Idol, and the Countrey worſhip: it can purchaſe all things, defend all things, and confound all things: And mad men travell over the world, to gain this folly, this faſhion: Who is not a true Fox, is but a beaſt of baſe eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>This is the worlds cuſtome, and what will become of the uſe, the wiſe man can hardly judge or imagine: Onely that theſe hainous ſins of falſhood, Theft, Murther and Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, can never walk but hand in hand with Iudgment: From which I heartily pray that the hand of the Higheſt will defend us, and make us walk in thoſe paths which ſhall be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to vertue and piety. With which I conclude, ſince theſe miſdeeds are not fit Theames for me to treate of, ſince at the laſt day every one is ſure to give an account for his own bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
               <p>WIth <hi>Reynard</hi> all his friends and Kinsfolks to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of forty, took their leave alſo of the King, and went away with the Fox, who was no little glad creature tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he had ſped well, and ſtood ſo far in the Kings favour: for now he had power enough to advance whom he pleaſed, and pull down any that envied his fortune.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:80"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>The Fox went in to Dame <hi>Ermeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> his wife, who wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed him with great tenderneſs: And to her and her children he related at large, all the wonders which had befallen him at the Court: and miſt no tittle or circumſtance therein. Then grew they proud that his Fortune was ſo excellent: and the Fox ſpent his days from thenceforth (with his Wife and Children) in great joy and content.</p>
               <p>Now whoſoever ſhall relate unto you (of the Fox) more or leſſe then you have heard: I would not wiſh you to build any faith upon his reports. Onely this which you have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy heard or read, you may believe at your beſt pleaſure: Or if any refuſe, he ſhall notwithſtanding be accounted an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, ſince he that onely ſaw it, may beſt give credit unto it; and yet many in this world believe the things they have not ſéen.</p>
               <p>Beſides, there are many Plays, both Comick and Morall, which figure out things that never were, onely to make uſe and benefit of the example: That men may thereby the better ſhun Vice, and purſue Vertues. In like manner, this Book, though it contain but matter of jeſt and ſport, yet if he look ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly thereinto, he may haply find much Moral matter and wiſdome, worth his conſideration. Goodneſs nor any Good man ſhall he find in it diſreputed, for all things are generally ſpoke, and every man may take his own part as his Conſcience ſhall inſtruct him: If any man find himſelf too much oppreſſed, let him ſhake it off with amendment: If any man be clear, let him hold on his path, and av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yd ſtumbling: And if any take diſtaſt or offence, let him not blame me, but the Fox, for it is onely his language. But if all things ſuit to my wiſh'd imiginations, I ſhall then be encouraged to ſalute the world with a ſecond part: clad in ſome neater Engliſh, déeper matter, and if not more, yet every whit as pleaſant Morals.</p>
               <div type="moral">
                  <head>The Morall.</head>
                  <p>By theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours done to the Fox by the Lion, is ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t ſeldom one good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e cometh with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he that hath once a chieve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſame and renown, to him will the world fly, and dignity on dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſhall be heaped upon him: as on the contrary part, be that is once fallen, either in ſtate or repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, it is a thing of much difficulty to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e him advanced without mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle; for worldly men are ſaid to be like Dogs, which when one of their own kinde is down, all the reſt will fall upon him and worrie him. But wiſe men, or good men (for both are ſcarce) are ſaid to be like Hogs; which when one of their kinde is down, all the reſt will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently aſſiſt and help him. For any thing elſe conteined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is either Moralized by the ſpeeches of the Fox, or elſe by the Author.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35919:81"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:81"/>
            <head>A Table of the Contents of all The CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>HOW the Lyon Proclaimed a ſolemne feaſt at his Court: And how <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf and his wife, and <hi>Curtiſe</hi> the Hound, made the firſt complaint of <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox. Chap. 1.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock ſpake for <hi>Reynard</hi> to the King. Chap. 2.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Cauntecleere</hi> the Cock complained of <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox. Chap. 3.</item>
               <item>The Kings anſwer to the Cocks complaint, and how they ſung the Dirge. Chap. 4.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Bruine</hi> the Bear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with <hi>Reynard</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:35919:82"/>
               <item>How the Fox came to the Court, and how he excuſed himſelf. Chap. 10.</item>
               <item>How the Fox was arreſted, and judged to death. Chap. 11.</item>
               <item>How the Fox made his confeſſion before the King. Chap. 12.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox was honoured of all Beaſts by the Kings commandment. Chap. 13.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Iſegrim</hi> and his wife <hi>Arſwind</hi> had their Shoos pluckt off for <hi>Reynard</hi> to wear to <hi>Rome</hi> Chap. 14.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Kaywarp</hi> the Hare was ſlain by <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox, and his head ſent by the Ram to the King. Chap. 15.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ram and his linege were given to the Bear and the Wolf. Chap. 16.</item>
               <item>How the King was angry at theſe complaints, took coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell for revenge, and how <hi>Reynard</hi> was forewarned of <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock. Chap. 17.</item>
               <item>How the Fox repenting his ſins, doth make confeſſion, and is abſolved by the Brock. Chap. 18.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox excuſed himſelf before the King, and the Kings anſwer. Chap. 19.</item>
               <item>How dame <hi>Rukenaw</hi> anſwered for the Fox to the King, and of the parable ſhe told. Chap. 20.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Reynard</hi> excuſed himſelf of <hi>Kaywards</hi> death, and all other imputations; got the Kings favour, and made a relation of certain Jewels. Chap. 21.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Reynard</hi> made his peace with the King, and how <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf complained of him again. Chap. 22.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Iſegrim</hi> profered his Glove to <hi>Reynard</hi> to fight with him which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and how <hi>Rukenaw</hi> adviſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chap. 23.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:82"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35919:83"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
